Good afternoon and welcome to the um
September 21st um public services
committee. Uh we are so glad that you're
able to join us here in council chambers
and for those of you that are on the
line on um zoom as well. Um please make
sure that you silence your cell phones.
Um if you are here in the chambers with
us uh put them on manners mode please.
We also if you would like to speak if
you'll approach the podium on either
side we're set up to take your comments.
Um and we will have a 3inut um public
comment period um after the following
the staff report. Please understand that
sometimes developers and other
individuals are included as part of that
staff report. Um, please identify
yourself when you approach the podium.
And,
>> [clears throat]
>> um, if you're calling in through Zoom,
uh, Jennifer will recognize you if
you'll use the virtual hand and then she
will tell you when, uh, she has made it
possible for you to speak to us. Um,
with that, Jennifer, if you Oh, I'm
sorry. Go ahead. Madam Chair, Madam
Chair,
>> I move to suspend the rules to hear item
number 21 first on the agenda.
Due to the anticipated length of agenda
today, I would ask the committee
consider handling item 21 first to allow
the committee to hear from the
consultant on the comprehensive climate
action plan.
>> Okay. We have a motion by Councilman
Crave to move item number 21 to the
first position on our agenda today. Is
there a second?
>> Second.
>> Okay. Is there any discussion?
>> Hearing none, all in favor say I. I.
opposed. Okay, we will move item number
21 to the beginning item on our agenda
to accommodate the consultants who are
going to be uh joining us. So, Jennifer,
if you'd like to read item number 21,
please. Number 21, resolution adopting a
comprehensive climate action plan in
accordance with the environmental
protection ay's climate pollution
reduction planning grant awarded to the
city.
Okay. And if we can have a staff report,
please.
Chair, members of the committee, Charles
Bloom, planning de development director.
Thank you very much for moving this item
up. We do have consultants with Lotus
Sustainability that are on the Zoom
call. It's a little bit easier for them
to um understand when their item will be
heard with the other ones that'll have
significant discussion likely. Um the
comprehensive climate action plan is a
plan for the MSA that's a metropolitan
statistical area for the city. Um this
plan has been completed in accordance
with resolution 6388 which was adopted
on February 26 of 2024. Um that was when
we received this grant for $1 million to
complete uh this project. I want to note
that not the entirety of this um less
than 50% of that was um spent regarding
this project. The biggest takeaway of
this plan is it really did a windshield
survey and a and a lot of outreach in
our community to identify um where our
greenhouse gas emissions were coming
from. And one of the biggest takeaways
was approximately 18% of the greenhouse
gases uh that were created within the
community um those were transportation
related. Um so a lot of the the
recommendations that are within this
report um are ones that we're already
dealing with. Those are um items such as
improving building efficiency, managing
water use, expanding our transportation
connections, reducing landfill waste,
improving housing options, and preparing
our workforce for um new industries. Um
there are a lot of recommendations in
this report. These are all
recommendations. Um and these are
intended to help guide our growth. Um
the some of the key elements about this
plan and uh I'd like to note that this
is really good timing because it comes
as our comprehensive plan kicks off is
we can continue to expand on some of
those items and see if we would like to
make those um more um policy related.
There is a section in this plan you'll
note um you you'll see it says a letter
from the the city to the citizens. Um
that is a one-page document that really
describes um some of the changes we're
seeing in the community when it comes to
greenhouse gases. Um notably um when
this plan kicked off, we didn't have a
lot of the proposals with uh data
centers and some of the energy sources
that come with those. Um those were new
items that came up during this plan.
Um, I do want to say one of the primary
goals of this plan, um, is really to set
us up to be able to apply for federal
grants, a variety of different grants
that would help carry out some of the
goals. Um, those could be grants such
as, uh, grants for municipal facilities
to help with, um, the energy efficiency,
uh, things that, uh, could also be
things like active transportation
infrastructure. that would be bicycle
lanes, uh pedestrian pathways, those
types of items and also sustainable
waste management initiatives. Um that's
my real high level overview of this
plan. Um there are a lot of details.
Again, I want to note that this is a
plan. None of these are uh changes and
if there were any changes that were
implemented because of this plan, it
would require governing body action. I
vote for any questions that you may have
and the consultants are online and they
can provide additional detail on this
and they can answer any specific
questions to the technical aspects of
this plan.
>> Thank you. Uh Councilman Crave
Chairwoman through
Could you speak to the
thought I had it there could you speak
to the impact of the data centers?
mentioned it briefly, but um you know
last week there was a a large meeting uh
discussing transportation as a result of
that or potentially as a result of that,
but I'm also we've heard issues with
potential air quality. Um
does this report give us a baseline? Um
how can we use it to this the
community's benefit uh as it as it
addresses those issues? Thank you,
>> chair. Three to council member Crave.
Um, I would respectfully defer that to
the consultant. I think he'll have a
better knowledge me to better answer
that question.
>> Any other questions from committee for
staff?
Okay. Um, is it Tom Herod?
>> That is correct. Chair.
>> Great.
>> Hello,
>> Mr. Herod. You should be able to speak
now.
>> I can. Thank you, Madam Chair. And uh my
name is Tom Herd. I'm with Lotus
Engineering Sustainability. We are the
consulting firm that completed the work
on the EPA's CPRG comprehensive climate
action plan. Uh to answer your your
question, Councilman Craves, uh the one
benefit of the timing of this, while
unfortunately we are not able to pull in
any existing uh data centers that uh
were in the community, this uh this
baseline assessment covered 2023, it
does give us that sort of baseline
approach. So should the city want to do
additional um inventorying of energy and
emissions uh this could be the
comparable baseline to have that pre and
post comparison for any any new emerging
technology like data centers that that
are coming online now. Thank you.
>> Any other questions for the consultant?
>> Are you going to give us an interview or
sorry an overview Mr. Herod?
Uh, madame chair, uh, thank you for the
question. Uh, Councilman Fres, not at
this time. Uh, we we do have, uh, the
packet that was prepared for council
today. Um, we are prepared to answer any
questions that might come up after
review of that uh, at additional
sessions of council, but um, do not have
a a full presentation today.
>> Okay. Thank you, Mr. Herod. Um, I'm
hopeful that we might this is a lengthy
document. um and very slippery because
of all the color. But um I'm hopeful
that we might be able to have a work
session at some point to talk about this
that there's a lot of information in
here. So Councilman Crave is that might
be a possibility as president of
council.
Okay. Okay. Um any at this point we will
go out for um public comment.
Okay. Is there anyone online for public
comment? I don't see anyone with their
hand raised.
Okay. Uh public comment is closed. So,
um I would entertain a motion.
>> Sure.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion from Councilman Crrave
and a second from Councilman Lebourne to
adopt. Um, is there any discussion?
>> Yes, Councilman Crave. Oh, sorry.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I'm gonna I'm going to
vote for this today. I have not had a
chance to review it. Um, realizing that
there's going to be more opportunities
down the road should there be issues.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Councilman Leborn.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. I speak in
favor of the adoption here uh because
this is really a fortuitous coincidence.
This is something that is going to bring
us expertise that we don't have and that
really can take a look at an incredibly
different situation in South Cheyenne.
That development of those data centers,
the power plants, the uh all that go
with it definitely are going to be
impacting what we do. I have heard uh
perhaps we could have another uh reading
element down there but uh obviously this
is coming along in a good time and I
would uh point out that we need to take
this seriously. It is uh air pollution
is a very complex
and uh
an an airshed is a gets results from a
variety of places and this is where we
really need to listen to the experts and
uh make some better decisions because
uh the changes that are occurring in
South Cheyenne with the data centers and
the power plants are tremendous. And so
uh I certainly welcome uh this expertise
and would point out that a work session
would be very beneficial. Thank you.
>> Any other comments from the dis
>> and Jennifer this document will be
attached to the agenda for next Monday
night's meeting. Is that correct? Yeah.
So um thank you. Okay. Hearing no
further discussion. All in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed.
This item will move forward with a
recommendation to approve. Uh next item
which will be number seven on our
agenda. Number seven, ordinance third
reading annexing to the city of
Cheyenne, Wyoming, land west of Roundtop
Road and adjacent to HappyJack Road.
Okay. Staff report please.
Chair, members of committee, Connor
White Planning and Development
Department. Uh this item is best known
as the Cox Ranch annexation. Um, this is
on third reading. This does include both
the Cox Ranch land as well as the city's
water treatment plan out there. Um, I've
got no further updates. There hasn't
been any more public comment that our
department has received at this time.
>> Thank you. Is there are there any
questions for staff?
>> Okay, hearing none or seeing none, we
will go out for public comment. Is there
anyone who is here who would like to
make public comment on the Cox rack? Cox
Ranch annexation. And again, we are only
talking about the annexation at this
point.
>> Madam Chair, thank you. Tom Gissmeer,
Vio West Group. Um,
wanted to thank the council and thank
the public for all of the input and the
opportunity we've had to discuss this
project over the last few months.
uh we have hoped to have been a good
example uh leading the leading the way
in transparency and and public outreach.
We're going to continue to do that. Uh
we're in fact working on our October and
November openhouse events and we'll
continue to do those.
Um
I am happy to take any questions. Um I
am also happy to leave a few comments
until the zoning portion as well. Thank
you,
>> Jack O'Neal with uh the development as
well and just wanted to say thank you
for the time today and remind anyone who
would like to reach out to please reach
out to Wyoming at
skyboxstatcenterers.com
and I'll save any further comment for
the zoning. Thank you.
Is there any other public comment on the
annexation?
Is there anyone online?
>> Okay. Hearing none or seeing none, I
would entertain a motion.
>> Chairwoman, I move to approve on third
and final reading.
>> Second. We have a motion from Councilman
Crave and a second from Dr. Renie um to
approve this um annexation on third and
final reading. Is there any discussion?
>> Councilman Lebornne.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. Um I have
really benefited from my uh
communication with these folks who are
preparing this uh annexation and it they
have really helped me uh take a look at
the issues that I have in terms of the
water question of the release of that
water from the uh Cherard treatment
plant which we are also annexing. So
that area has some unique
characteristics there that uh we're
going to be meeting about tomorrow with
those uh subject matter experts and
coming up with some ideas that uh can
benefit uh both the land the repairarian
zone and uh really the Crow Creek itself
which is where that water ends up. So I
think that we've uh come a long way in
communication about this. I look forward
to continuing that and uh I believe that
we've established some uh voluntary
benchmarks of communication that'll be
very useful. So um I speak in favor of
passage right now. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Any other discussion
hearing? None. All in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed. This item will move forward
with recommendation to approve on third
and final reading at the next meeting of
the council. Next item, please. Number
eight, ordinance, third reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, establishing
establishing the zoning classification
of AG agricultural MP public for land
annex to the city of Cheyenne located
west of Round Top Road and adjacent to
HappyJack Road. Okay. And just as uh the
mayor commonly reminds us, anytime we
annex land into the city, we do uh try
to give it a a
zone that is similar to what it had in
the county um prior to zoning it uh for
um the enduse development. Um so with
that, we would entertain a staff report.
Chair, members of the committee, Conor
White, Planning and Development
Department.
As our chair mentioned, uh yes, when we
annex land, we do try to establish the
closest city zone to what it currently
has or current uses that are uh the land
currently has. So, with that, with the
Fox Ranch portion, um staff would
recommend the AG zone agricultural and
then for the city-owned parcel Public.
Uh again, this is on third reading.
Staff has had no further public comment
on this specific item. Uh I am available
for questions.
>> Thank you. Are there any questions for
staff from the council? Okay.
Hearing none or seeing none, uh we would
go out for public comment.
Is there anything online? Okay. Hearing
or seeing no public comment, we'll close
the public comment. Um, I would
entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I would move to
approve 13.
>> We have a motion to approve by Dr.
Renie, a second by Councilman Lebornne.
Is there any discussion?
All in favor say I opposed. This item
will move forward with a recommendation
to approve at the next meeting of the
council on third and final reading. Next
item, please. Number nine, Ordinance,
third reading, amending the official
zoning map of the city of Cheyenne,
changing the zoning classification for
land located west of Roundtop Road and
adjacent to Habjack Road from AG
Agricultural to BP Business Park. And so
this is that follow-up zoning where the
um developer or the land owner would
like to change that to business park
from the zone we just gave it, which was
agricultural. And so we would um
entertain a staff report at this point.
Chair, members of committee, Conor Way
Planning and Development Department. Uh,
this is an applicant requested zone
change from that established zone of AG
to BP Business Park. Um, I've got no
further new information and staff hasn't
had any additional public comment
specific to this item.
>> Okay. Any questions from a committee for
staff?
Okay. Hearing none or seeing none, we
will uh open up public comment.
Madame Chair, members of the council,
Tom Glymmeer, Bio West Group.
Uh, regarding the regarding the BP zone,
um, I understand that there's there have
been some questions or comments why, you
know, about uh, split zoning, uh, or
trimming down the zoning. Um, that that
wasn't feasible or an option for us. Um
we
uh favorably looked at the site in that
it has a lot of wetlands and
undevelopable land anyway that we
wouldn't be uh wouldn't be using or
couldn't use frankly. Uh so we
also and I if I if I speculate just a
little bit uh the the BP zone within the
city is a um if if I were a seller uh I
would proactively um see that as a as a
way of adding value to my land given the
adjacent infrastructure and uh utilities
and being near the uh water treatment
plant and power lines etc all out there.
So being being adjacent to the North
Range Business Park, I think is a is a
valuable uh asset to uh to land out
there. So if uh again, if I were
speculating, I think that you know, it
is a it is an owner petitioned
uh process, they whether or not we
whether or not we were the end buyer or
end user um there there could be could
be a number of uses in that zone that
that would be valuable. And um so I
think as a as a seller that would be the
calculus that I would do. Um
again I just want to reiterate our our
gratitude to the council uh and and to
the public for going through this
process and and making this project
better in a lot of ways and uh we're
very excited to uh have the opportunity
to continue to do that and continue to
set the bar high. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Council
Jack O'Neal with the development skybox
data centers. Thank you all very much
for the time today and thank you for
everyone who uh came out on behalf of us
as well including our neighbors um the
Eley's and on behalf of the Cox. We have
uh um Attorney Gaywood House as well. Uh
as we've mentioned uh on the first and
second reading and a few public service
councils before, we've worked with all
of our neighbors to get this into a
great spot. We've had five public
service or public meetings so far. Um,
as Tom and I mentioned, we would like to
continue to host those regardless of uh
approval or not next week through
October, November, December, and uh, you
know, hopefully for years to come after
that as this development progresses. Uh,
and should anyone have any questions,
please again feel free to reach out to
Wyoming skyboxstaters.com.
That's an email address
and Tom. We also have a phone number and
happy to set up some time uh over the
phone or over coffee or uh or beer as
well. But thank you all for the time and
the effort and here to answer any
questions should there be any from uh
from y'all or also be afterwards from
the public. Thank you.
>> You might have a few more takers with
adult beverages being offered.
>> So
we're fun.
>> Any other public comment?
Is there any online Jennifer? I don't
see anyone with their hand raised. Oh,
Mr. Eley,
>> Madame Chair, uh we don't see or have
any opposition to this zone change and
potential multi-use which would be
beneficial for us at the King Ranch and
probably for the business park. Uh you
honored our request to not annex a
portion of the ranch in. We're going to
continue to put that into a conservation
easement. uh it should be done hopefully
before the end of the year. Uh so it
kind of makes it an entire package. So
at this point we're pleased with the
action.
>> Thank you.
>> Good morning.
>> Okay. Gabe Woodhouse with uh Woodhouse
Road and Ames and Brennan on behalf of
Cox Ranches LLC and the Chalk Bluff uh
Historic Preservation Foundation out of
Colorado. I have been working with
Skybox and Via West regarding the
security of the mausoleum which you guys
have heard rec state many times was sort
of an aberration in terms of what
happened with the family and us being
kind of blindsided when we heard this
was part of the annexation process. But
I would like to say that um my clients
Mark T. Cox IV and Beverly Cox Black are
very happy with what has happened and um
feel that the mausoleum will be
protected into perpetuity and they've
been extremely generous uh conscientious
and sympathetic about our plight. So we
really appreciate working with them and
this won't happen if you know the
annexation doesn't go through next
Monday. So thank you.
>> Thank you. Is there any other public
comment?
in the room.
Anything online, Jennifer?
Okay, last call.
Okay, I would entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I would move to
approve on third reading.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion from Dr. Renie and a
second from Councilman Crrave um to
approve on third and final reading. Is
there any discussion,
>> Madam Chair? Yes, Dr. Renie.
>> I first of all, I I want to thank and
congratulate um Tom and Jack for working
with I know if you've probably all seen
the map that Miss Woodhouse has that
shows the 35 dedicated acres that
they've given for the mausoleum to make
that site secure for the family in
perpetuity. So, um I do want to thank
them for working on that. Um because
that was going to be a sticking point
for most of us last spring when this
first came up. Um I brought up the
question with Mr. Glymmer and I also
brought up with our staff on the split
zoning. Um and and I appreciate Mr.
Gliss Meer's explanation that the land
owner thinks it has more value to them
if it's a business park zone. But
honestly, as as one that sat up here and
and taken a few with the rest of us and
taken a few arrows, I think it would
have been much more reassuring to the
Rolling Hills community if after
um after we zoned it the area P and A
that then we just carved out the 200
acres that they intend on using as the
business park and left the rest of it a
because I think if the neighborhood had
known that 83% of it still would take an
egg zone, they would have and a little
um would not have been quite as
concerned as what they initially were.
So I think that created a lot more work
for the people from Skybox Vio West and
created a lot more headaches for us. So
I just wanted to make that comment.
>> Thank you, Councilman Crave.
>> Madame Chair, I would also like to thank
the developers. uh they were the first
first developers that I that I'm aware
of that put together an agreement with
the city that outlines specifically how
they will function regarding a lot of
different issues. Everything from
lighting, sound, uh water, uh snow
removal, on and on and on. And that
template is now being used by other
developers. And I think you know
listening to the public uh there were
always concerns that there were no there
was nothing in writing holding the
developer to these standards. U again
this was the first developer to do that.
We're now working with another developer
uh that will be up later today uh that
is also u willing and able and and in
the process of doing that as well. So um
we are as as we go through these
processes, we are learning, we are
listening, we are trying to put
everything that we can into that
agreement. So I would just like to thank
everybody um staff, everybody that that
has worked on that document. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Any other comments? Dr.
Renie. Yeah, madam chair ch ch ch ch ch
ch ch ch ch ch ch ch ch ch ch ch ch ch
ch ch ch I was gonna I forgot to add and
then my colleague from W two pretty much
said what I wanted to say but um you
know as we all know the history I think
our first data centers were fairly small
and going back over 20 years ago. Um the
first one of any size we had was a
Microsoft data center in 2012 and there
wasn't a lot of activity until recently
and then we kind of became inundated
with with proposals. But I did I did
want to echo what my colleague said and
tell the public that we have learned as
we've been doing this and we have
listened and we are trying to add more
guard rails to protect the community and
protect protect our constituents. So,
it's not like I mean I think most of us
want up here want to see the continued
economic development and economic
diversification and and the jobs and and
potential benefits that come with this.
But again, we are try we are learning as
we go along and and we are trying to add
more guardrails. So, I I did want to
bring that up too. Thank you.
>> Yeah, I think one of the challenges
always is that technology is changing as
well. So, it's always a learning
process.
Any other comments?
Okay. Um, we have a motion and a second.
Um, all in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed. This item will move forward
with a recommendation to approve on
third and final reading at the next
meeting of the council. Next item,
please. Number 10, ordinance, second
reading, annexing to the city of
Cheyenne, Wyoming, land located south of
Interstate 80, southeast of Otto Road
and west of Interstate 25. Staff report
please.
Madam Chair, Morgan Dennis, Planning and
Development. This is an annexation for
roughly 652.67
acres of land generally located south of
Interstate 80, southeast of Auto Road
and west of Interstate 25, also known as
the Hitching Post District.
The land proposed to be annexed is
contiguous to current city limits.
Specifically, the larger parcel is
64.71%
and the smaller parcel is 80.668%.
All city services and utilities
currently available to residents of the
city will be provided to the resident to
the properties of this annex land.
Extending water and sewer will increase
the health and safety of those in this
area of the community. The area to be
annexed is inside the urban service
boundary and designated as rural
agricultural open space and parks and
mixeduse employment by the future land
use map. This type of development is
best supported by being within city
limits and connected to city services.
The public hearing for this annexation
was held on September 14th, 2026.
This annexation is also accompanied by
an assigned zoning, future land use map
amendment, a zone change, and later a
plat. And I stand for questions. Okay.
Are there any questions from committee?
Uh Dr. Renie, you had your letter.
>> Oh, sorry. Councilman Crave.
>> Yes. Uh through you, Madam Chairwoman.
Uh M. Dennis, I would I would just like
to reaffirm the five major requirements
by state statute are are documented
here. those being um
um services are available um approximate
to the city uh makes sense to develop it
with city water and sewer etc. Can you
kind of just hit those bullets for us
and confirm that for the record? Thank
you.
Sorry, I'm pulling it up real quick.
>> I think it's 15142.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. So
madam chairman through you to uh
Councilman Crave. Um the five um
requirements are an annexation of the
area is for the protection, health,
safety and welfare of the persons
residing in the area in the city or
town. So that is the first requirement.
Um so this annexation would increase the
health, safety and welfare of the any
future development in this area by being
connected to city water and sewer rather
than a well or having septic tanks out
there. Um
this would also have access to the fire
department which is accredited and
uh whenever it comes to city development
a the city often has a higher standard
for development than developments out in
the county. The second requirement is
the urban development of the area sought
to be annexed would constitute a
natural, geographical and economic,
economal and social part of the annexing
city or town. Um, as I previously
stated, they are uh really close to the
city. Uh the third one is the area
sought the area being annexed is logical
and feasible addition to the annexing
lander city with the extension of
utilities. Um the there are existing
utilities in the area that can be
extended upon annexation.
Um the fourth criteria is the area is
contiguous which is kind of a repeat of
two. So,
and the city or town does not own or
operate its own um
let's see. No, that's not electric
utility.
>> And then we have Yeah, that's okay.
The city or town does not own or operate
its own electric utilities. Its
governing body is prepared to issue one
or more franchisees as necessary to
serve the annexed area. We are we are
prepared to issue all those utility
franchises and the six criteria is the
certified mailing requirement which we
have met.
>> Thank you madam chair.
>> You any other questions from committee
for staff?
Okay. U Mr. Emmens madam chair Brad
Emmens AVI uh agent for the owner and
applicant on this currently Swan Ranch
LLC and Doug Samuelson. This is an owner
initiated annexation. I I believe there
were some questions that came up at the
public hearing we tried to discuss, but
one of the reasons it's split is because
the city bisects the ownership areas
where the the roads going down to the
area are. So that's the reason there's a
split in that annexation boundary. Um
and we are bringing both sides in so
that the roadway can be developed uh in
the city uh as we move forward. um be
happy to answer any other annexation
questions, but we will be ready to speak
at the zoning as well.
>> Okay, thank you.
Okay, we'll go out for public comment.
Is there any public comment regarding
the um pitching post district
annexation?
Anything online, Jennifer? I don't see
anything.
Hearing or seeing none, I would
entertain a motion. Madam Chairwoman,
>> second.
>> Okay, we have a motion by Councilman
Labour and a second by Councilman
Crrave. Um, any discussion? Councilman
Renie.
>> Madam Chairman, I just want to say that
um the state has pledged 15 million
towards this project. Leeds has pledged
15 million towards this project. Our
voters have voted $5 million towards
this project. Um, so it's going to
happen and it's going to be built and it
is going to be a great asset for
Cheyenne
and it would just be silly if we didn't
keep it in the city. So I see no reason
to even to oppose this. So thank you.
>> Thank you, Councilman Crave. I would
just I would also like to add that, you
know, from a
from a cultural standpoint, from a um
visitors standpoint, it this is a in my
opinion is a perfect location. It's
going to have very high visibility.
Um it just seems like it's a natural fit
with our our history and uh I'm so
excited to have these these folks move
here and uh really look forward to uh
following the progress and I agree with
Dr. Renie uh in my opinion this should
be part of the city uh with all of the
utilities and fire and uh police and
everything else we have to go with it.
Thank you.
>> Thank you Councilman Labbornne.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. And I want to
uh particularly thank the Samuelsons.
This is something that is so colossal
and that will bring such results over
time that it was uh surprising to me
when it began and now we realize that we
are this far along as has been mentioned
great support from a number of uh
government uh public entities. I do want
to recognize that there's going to be
some real effort there by the Department
of Transportation to improve access to
that uh that area. It's uh
got some challenges now and it certainly
needs some serious attention as we go
along. On a personal level, I uh look
forward to uh the eventual placement of
the Hall of Fame since there are a
couple of Hall of Fame honores that were
my mentors in my rodeo career and I'm
sure that uh that goes for a lot of
people who uh participate in Cheyenne
Frontier Days and look forward to uh
that effort. So, this is uh something
that's going to really really emphasize
who we are and I think that that'll be
very useful in our visit in our visitors
promotion. Thank you.
>> Any other comments? Uh, Councilman
Renie.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I also Oh, when I was
giving those dollar figures, we'd
already voted in the past to pledge 1
million of city funds towards the
project already as well. Um, I also want
to give kudos to Cheyenne Leeds. They've
taken a lot of heat lately by saying and
being criticized for only bringing us
data centers. They have worked they and
their consultant have worked on this for
a long time and you know they're just
doing trying to do what brings jobs and
brings economic benefit to Cheyenne and
this will be a big economic driver. So
thank you.
>> Any other comments from committee
hearing or seeing none I would entertain
a motion or all in favor say I. Sorry. I
>> opposed. Okay. This item will be move
forward with a recommendation to approve
at the next meeting of the council. Next
item, please. Number 11, ordinance
second reading, amending the official
zoning map of the city of Cheyenne,
establishing the zoning classification
of AG agricultural and LI light
industrial for land annex to the city of
Cheyenne located south of Interstate 80,
southeast of Otto Road, and west of
Interstate 25.
>> Okay. Staff report, please. So this is
the assigned zoning for the hitching
post district. The current zoning of the
land it for the largest parcel is
overland PUD and county light industrial
for the smaller parcel. The future land
use map has designate these these areas
as agricultural rural open space and
parks and mixeduse employment. But there
is an amendment submitted for the future
land use map to change to community
business that will be discussed later.
Staff considered five potential zones
for this area due to the overland PUD
for the largest parcel. They were
business park, light industrial, heavy
industrial, community business, and
agricultural. The smaller parcel is
already zoned county light industrial
and staff recommends it maintains the
light industrial designation within city
zoning. The larger parcel required a
more thorough consideration since the
Overland PUD placed several different
designations within this parcel. The PUD
placed industrial, business, and open
space designations within the parcel.
Due to the ambiguity of the land uses
within the PUD, staff considered the
existing use of the parcel for city
zone. The current use is vacant, vacant,
or agricultural. Thus, staff recommends
AG agricultural for the assigned zoning
of the larger parcel.
Planning Commission heard this item on
September 8th and recommends approval
and there has been no public comment
regarding the assigned zoning and I
stand for questions. Thank you. Any
questions for staff from the committee?
Okay, we will open it up for public
comment. Is there anyone who would like
to make public comment on this?
and anyone online.
Okay. Hearing or seeing none, I would
entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I would move to
approve on second reading.
>> We have a motion from Councilman Crave
and a second from Councilman Renie. Um
any discussion?
All in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed. This item will move forward
with a recommendation to approve at the
next meeting of the council. Next item,
please. Number 12, ordinance, second
reading, amending the official zoning
map of the city of Cheyenne, changing
the zoning classification for land
located south of Interstate 80 southeast
of Otto Road and west of the of
Interstate 25 from AG agricultural and
LI industrial light industrial to BP
business park.
>> Report. Madame Chair, Morgan Dennis,
Planning and Development. So, this is a
zone change for the Hitching Post
District. The parcels will have the
zones of agricultural and light
industrial. The [snorts] proposed zone
change is to BP business park. The B the
business park is applicable in areas
near the interstate interchange or
intersections of major collectors and
principal arterials. While the business
zone typically district typically has
the development patterns of Swan Ranch
and North Range Business Park with lower
intensity commercial and service uses
are typically secondary or support the
industrial developments in the area.
The BPU zone will be undergoing changes
and it's allowed agricultural uses.
Um
okay. And the use the end use identified
for this area the PRCA um hall of fame
often needs um equestrian needs
development for equin events and
activities. So with this change to the
BP zone it would make it more applicable
than say the CB or any other zone. And I
stand for question. Oh, the planning
commission heard this uh on September
8th and recommends approval and there
has been no uh public comment regarding
this zone change and I stand for
questions.
>> Thank you. Are there any questions for
staff? Dr. Renie. Madam Chan, I I think
Morgan just answered my question and
that was
when when in the past when we've dealt
with with the BP zone, we've I've been
thinking Swan Ranch, North Range
Business Park, now data centers and that
was I was curious as to how this complex
fit into the BP zone better than any
other zone. So,
Councilman's Crave
Chairwoman through you. Um,
I understand there was some there I'm
not sure it's through the zoning. Um,
but there might be some type of a
restriction for data centers in this
area. Have have you heard of that at
all?
>> Uh, Mr. Emmens evidently can answer that
if he'd turn on his mic.
>> Um, Madam Chair, through you. Brad
Emmens, AVI, again, agent for the
applicant, Swan Ranch LLC, Doug Samson,
and Doug's here to speak of his uh
desires. So, I'll let him kind of speak
specifically to that um because there's
a few other things um that he is looking
at as well. I would also point out that
uh the people here when you're leaving,
there's a poster out in the lobby that's
been out there for two or three weeks.
Heirs and Associates has um also been
hired to do some master planning for
what people want to see, different
ideas. There's a QR code on there if the
public wishes to present uh other
thoughts that could be things that could
be developed on the parcel. And so um
with Doug's approval, we obviously are
moving forward with that as well. So um
I'd be happy to answer any other BP
questions, but would like to let Doug
speak to the other items.
>> Thank you. Sounds like another item for
a work session. [laughter] We're
building up that list.
>> That is
>> That's right. Good afternoon,
>> Madam Chair, council. I'm Doug
Samuelson. I'm the manager of Swan Ranch
LLC. And um this area was a winter
pasture for sheep for decades, for
probably for a hundred years. And I
swore we would never develop this. It's
going to stay that way. Well, leadeds
brought PRCA in and they picked this
spot. And of course, I'm flexible. I
changed my mind. I said, "Okay, we're
going to do this." Cuz you know, when
you come into Cheyenne, you see if you
come from the east, you see big boxes,
you see the refinery, you see data
centers. Um, if you come from the south,
you see two casinos, which, you know,
that's not how I like to shine to be
known. If you come from the west, you go
through those uh wind parks or wind
things box stores. But I wanted to have
one nice place in this town where you
come in and it'll it'll be something
we're proud of. We're not sure exactly
how it's going to be. We know the Hall
of Fame, PRCA of Statue Park. Well, um
BP gives you a lot of they can have a
lot of things in there that um I don't
like. uh firecracker stands, uh wind
farms, solar. I don't really against
data centers. There's a different but
not on us. Um that's not going to happen
um in this area. Uh so um we I we have
some covenants drawn up. Our attorney is
John Mckenley and he's him and I have
had trouble for like three weeks getting
together. We each have a draft. We're
going to get together and merge that
draft. So, we have one draft um that
we'll show to the leads in the PRCA, but
some of the things we have in there are
um no fireworks stands, no wind farms,
no data centers, no um commercial solar
um and several other things. Uh and you
guys will get a chance to see those.
It'll be, you know, with the covenants
uh with the plaque. But um we were
tricked one time south of town, a
fireworks stand. There was a kind of a
he wasn't the most popular actor um with
firecracker stands and he was pulling
all kinds of things. He wanted to buy
one little lot down there and um we
didn't want it, but we were trying to
sell it. Um so we told him no. We told
him no a couple times. He made offers
and um he even said you'd want a big bag
of cash we'll give you. And I go away.
we don't want to deal with you. But um
so anyway, couple weeks later, the
realtor said, "We have an offer for um
cigar and cigarette and a vape store."
Go, well, that's better than fireworks.
So I signed it. That afternoon, it was a
straw buyer. He was moving um semis
loaded of fireworks there. So um we we
learned a lesson. Uh so in the deeds,
every deed and um in these covenants,
every paragraph shows the stuff that's
not allowed. So you can't say you didn't
see it. But in the deed also within the
deed, those are going to be repeated
with a revert clause. And um I think the
city has learned what a revert clause
does with uh the fire station over
across McCormack Junior High. Um and
it's pretty strict. uh we just don't
want to be tricked where um you know
somebody comes in and uh you know if you
want to see a strip club you're going to
have to go south of town. You're not
going to go there. Stuff like that. So
um uh we're really uh you know those are
I want something to be proud down there.
I don't know what's going to be there,
where it's going, but we're we're slow
walking it. I'm not in a hurry. Uh but
we are we still are going to be grazing
it this winter with sheep and um
there'll probably be some horses and
livestock out there uh with the PRC and
stuff which you know that's another
thing you know so we want grazing to be
allowed but um hopefully we have every
and I'm sure you guys will all get to
see these covenants when John and I get
it finalized and then we'll have one
draft that for review and um appreciate
all your support. Um, sorry I changed my
mind on uh when I said never say never
that doesn't mean ever never more
flexible. So uh but this is something
that uh I'm so proud of and and
Microsoft is paying for the sewer to go
through there too which is huge. Um and
uh you know we have some big support
from them. So I think it's going to be a
wonderful thing and uh I'm really
excited about it and hopefully I don't
know when uh Dante he's here. we know
when it's actually to break ground. I
think it's in two years. So, everybody's
moving fast and thanks to the city for
chipping in the money and uh we'll uh
we'll try to keep it a place that we're
all proud of and um I think you guys you
guys know me well enough that uh you
know once we give you our word, we're
going to do it. Uh we're not going to we
won't back out on that unless it's uh to
sell us to the PRCA.
But well, thanks for your time. Thank
you for your generosity and for being a
welcome your passion for our community.
>> Thank you.
>> Any other public comment?
Anything online?
Hey, not hearing or seeing anything. I
would entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I would move to
approve on second reading.
>> Okay. Thank you, Councilman Crave. We
have a motion from Councilman Se, a
second from Councilman Labbornne. Is
there any discussion?
>> All in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed. This item will move forward
with recommendation to approve at the
next meeting of the council.
13, ordinance, second reading, amending
the official zoning map of the city of
Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located south of
Interstate 80, east of Camp Stool Road
and north of HR Ranch Road from AG
Agricultural to BP Business Park. Okay.
Uh staff report, please.
Morgan Dennis, Planning and Development.
This is a zone change for approximately
73.87 87 acres of land located south of
Interstate 80 east of Camp Stool Road
and north of HR Ranch Road. The current
zoning of this parcel is AG
agricultural. The proposed zone is BP
business park. The future land use map
designates this area as community
business. This designation is meant to
focus on general retail and offices,
regional malls, hotels, and other
service businesses. Intensive in
industrial activities are not
appropriate. This designation is often
located at interstate interchange and
intersections of arterial or state
highways. This parcel sits at the
intersection of a state highway and
major collector/principal artery.
Surrounding zoning is CB and BP to the
north with commercial development.
County LU land use to the south with
agriculture and rural residential uses.
agricultural and heavy industrial to the
west and AG parcel. The AG parcel is
vacant and the HI parcel has a general
industrial use. The split zone of county
public and land use with a government
facility is to the east.
While this parcel cannot independently
qualify for the BP zone based on the
lack of acreage, a recent zone change to
the north to business park would allow
this parcel to join the rest of that
park to the north.
Uh this would expand the allowed uses on
the park on the parcel from agricultural
related uses to select service uses, a
variety of commercial uses and data
center development.
While staff is not aware of the inuse
for this parcel, any development would
need to meet the applicable UDC
standards. Uh staff has received public
comment regarding the zone change. I
believe there was a letter that should
have been sent to the council. Um
planning commission heard this on
September 8th and recommends denial and
I stand for questions.
>> Is there any question? Oh, Councilman
Crave.
>> Yes. Could we hear the uh reason for the
denial from the planning commission?
Miss Dennis.
Uh Madame Chairman to uh through you to
u Councilman Crave. The planning
commission uh denied based on two they
believe two review criteria were not
met. Um, one of them was the
uh public safety health and that
criteria. They believe it was not met
due to the um there is a important bird
area just south of this area on the
preferred ranch. And they and there was
public comment made at planning
commission that any development on this
property would disturb that IBA area.
What was the other?
And they also denied it based on review
criteria 2 which is compatibility of
surrounding properties. Uh they did not
believe any uh commercial development
would be compatible in this area.
>> Follow
through you, Madam Chairman. And how
about city staff? What's what's your
recommendation? If I read it correctly,
you recommend approval. Is that right?
>> Uh, Madam Chair, through you. Um, yes,
staff does recommend approval as it
meets as we believe it meets all the
review criteria.
>> Thank you.
>> Any other questions for staff? Dr.
Renie.
>> Madame Chairwoman, through you to our
staff. Um, when was this area annexed
into the city? Uh, Madam Chair, through
you. Uh, this was actually annexed in
2006.
So, it has been in the city for nearly
20 years.
>> Okay. And then I guess follow up because
you alluded to it um with with the area
immediately across the highway to the
north being developed for businesses um
services to travelers. I presume that at
some point it was viewed that that would
develop similarly on the south side. Uh,
madam chair through you. Yes, according
to all of our planning documents, that
was the
>> Yeah,
>> that's what I thought I'd heard. Thank
you.
>> Okay. Any other staff report? Any other
questions for staff?
>> Okay, we'll go into public comment.
We'll start over here and then we'll
come over to this side.
>> Um, madame chair, uh, Brad Emmens, uh,
AVI agent for the applicants HR land
company. Uh yeah, before you is a zone
change from AG to business park. As uh
staff pointed out, it's been long uh
believed that this land would be uh
commercially developed. Um and there has
been some um additional
utilities that are looking to go through
this area. The Archer complex uh future
sewer main uh needs to go through this
parcel. Um and so uh all the utilities
will be adjacent to it um very soon if
if that project moves forward. That's
what brought um the owners here uh to
get this the ball rolling on uh the
options for future development on the
parcel and uh we stand for any
questions. We do have some exhibits that
they would like to go over um but I will
let them uh present those to you.
>> Thank you sir.
Uh Matt Bowman. Um I'm a HR ranch
resident uh just south of the Archer
Fairgrounds. Um Madame Chair, council,
thank you for recognizing me. Um I've
been in information technology for three
decades. Made my livelihood on it. Not
opposed to data centers. Um I did I I
don't know exactly what I heard a little
bit of conflicting information about
possible utilization for this parcel. Um
but uh we have three data centers on the
north side of 80 uh Christensen Cam
Stool. We have a new one going on on the
south side. And I just want to exercise
a little bit of caution. Um
Chairman Crave pointed out uh cultural
compatibility with in respect to our
previous uh motion or ordinance. Uh I I
just want to be vigilant about uh the
way we're presenting the east side of
Cheyenne because it seems like coming in
that's what we see now. Um uh also the
second point I I'm not a geologist. I
don't uh you not going to make that
claim. Uh I hear a lot of anecdotal
stuff about uh Okala aquifer. Um I don't
know if that's uh urban legend or if
that's accurate that we are it's being
in a depletion state, but I just want to
be vigilant about that as well. Um thank
you council.
>> Thank you. Thanks for being here. Yes,
ma'am.
Hi, my name is Deborah Loam. Um, I'm one
of the managing members of the HR Land
Company. I'm pleased to be here today.
Um, I brought with me a few exhibits for
your review that might be helpful to
give a little sense of the location. I
know you know it well, but um, I thought
I would start out with, um, first
noting, well, as we noted that the, uh,
area to the north is currently Business
Park across I80. Um, our largest uh um
boundary on this property is Interstate
80 to the north. Our east boundary is
the Wild Dot Gravel Pit site. Our south
boundary is the Camptool Road and the
Wyoming Kerford Ranch. And the west
boundary is the Campill Road and uh
Plains Marketing. Um,
one of the things I wanted to point out
in the exhibit that uh is that we have
been approached as land owners uh for a
proposed BOPU East for water and sewer
to serve the uh ex hopeful expansion at
the Archer Ranch Complex. Um, as you can
see, our property is already subject to
significant easements for power and gas
uh lines uh already uh in uh uh they're
already in place. Um,
I also think it's very significant to
understand this property's location and
the speaking of the geology, we're a bit
of on on a bluff and I brought a exhibit
to explain how that works is, you know,
we have Interstate 80, we're a bit on a
bluff and then we run to um the HR Ranch
Road and then the land drops off
significantly and we drop down into the
Crow Creek area which I think we're all
quite familiar with And from our
perspective on our property on it, uh
it's very we actually can't see Crow
Creek. Um it's a significant drop down.
Um we don't believe the residents on the
Wyoming Herford Ranch actually can see
our property from that elevation. It's
just a drop. It's a significant drop
down. Um
and so we think that's actually
significant in considering you know
future use and the impacts in the area.
Um may answer any questions while I'm
here.
>> I would note that um all of you as
council people have the great big maps
that um have been provided
>> by I believe HR land company.
>> Yes. One I let me just caution you that
your three minutes is almost up. Um but
because um I think probably you were
hoping to present under staff
development or a staff report um we will
extend the time for you. I want to keep
it brief. You guys are very busy. But um
one thing I would uh actually want to
point out too is we do feel like we're
consistent in keeping with our use of
expanding into the business park. Um,
you know, our neighbors to the south,
the Wyoming Herford Ranch has has
recently transferred a 47 acre parcel
for a substation on their property,
which is adjacent to our property,
additional HR land property. Uh, not
this property, but property to the east.
So, we're not at the we are we are
definitely at the uh in the middle of it
out there. We're getting it from all
directions. Um, and we believe a
business park designation is the
appropriate use for future development
of this property.
>> Thank you.
>> Um, any questions from council? Uh, Dr.
Winnie.
Oh, I'm sorry. I thought you were
shaking your head. Yes. Okay. Thank you
so much. Looks like maybe another work
session topic going on here. Lordy.
Okay. Hi there.
>> Hi. Uh, my name is Vicky Haron. I live
at 2518 Windmill Road. I'm on the board
of the Cheyenne High Plains Ottabon
chapter. I am the important bird area
committee chair.
I will repeat myself from the September
8th uh testimony that we oppose the
zoning change request
um for three reasons. Um there is no end
use identified in the public documents
for this area. Um it's difficult to
determine whether it's really compatible
with um the uh nearby properties.
Um secondly, um there have been no
opportunities to discuss our concerns,
which they may not have known because
the important bird area has not really
received a lot of publicity.
It was identified over 20 years ago as
an important bird area for three
reasons. It provides essential habitat
for species of conservation concern
identified by the game and fish
department. It contains rare, unique or
exceptional habitat um that represents
our u local eco zone and it regularly
holds significant
concentrations of of congregating birds
which by the way is happening right now.
Millions of birds are flying through
here every night. This is an This is an
important bird area and it's Wyoming's
best important bird area. So, uh, you
know, it holds 275 species of birds. It
has all that great habitat. Um, so all
of that said, we feel like the uh
opportunity to
recognize that it's an important bird
area that it contains uh western
agricultural heritage viewshed and um
that the birds that migrate through the
Herford Ranch will migrate right through
that property or that parcel. um they to
undoubtedly forage on that parcel.
We don't have the data, but it's it's
directly adjacent. And um we just feel
like there would be um some
opportunities
for um [clears throat]
how do I say this? um
showing off [laughter] the agricultural
heritage of the area and the importance
of of birds and bird habitat in in our
part of the state.
>> Thank you so much.
>> I have a question.
>> Oh, sure. Councilman Crave,
>> real quick.
>> Okay.
>> If if you're opposed to this
development, what would you like to see
developed there?
>> Oh my gosh. Uh [laughter]
>> housing. Um
okay. Uh
I if it is to be developed with um and
the habitat uh changed from open space,
it be best to have uh development that
has very few lights. Uh lights at night
are a huge concern for birds. um
traffic, the least amount of traffic,
the less um uh disturbance to birds.
Um noise in general is anything that
doesn't have noise, lights. Yeah. So
right uh but a uh maybe some sort of um
small visitor center that welcomes
people uh to talk about the birds and
the agricultural heritage of the of this
part of the state. Um yeah something
that maybe a conservation easement to
we don't have anything.
>> Has has your group thought about
purchasing the property? We have not. We
have a board meeting tomorrow night and
we'll be talking about options here.
>> Any other questions?
>> Thank Thank you very much. I appreciate
>> Yeah, you're welcome. Um I have one
question.
>> So C. Okay. Thank you. Um my question uh
would be what number of acres would you
need in order to um if we were if the
developer were able to carve out a
number of acres uh for this important
bird area? What number of acres are
would that be required to uh maintain
this as an important bird area?
H that's a great question and I don't
have a specific answer but uh the part
that's immediately adjacent I don't know
exactly how far east it goes but those
birds are coming up they they're coming
up that hill m when they're migrating
north they have to get over that parcel
and then over the interstate and the new
maverick and stuff so so they they
definitely need that section and I I'm
sorry I can't tell you how many acres
that thank
pass it back to you.
>> Thank you.
>> Feeding.
>> Okay. Can I make one more point?
>> Sure. [laughter]
So, um the resident birds will are using
that parcel for foraging, right? So, you
have red tail hawks and swings hawks and
such that are um catching the small
mammals. you have the um meadowarks and
bluebirds and um
different kinds of sparrows residents
that are using that property or that
parcel I should call it. Um because it's
open space and it's native vegetation.
So the insects and small mammals and
everything else that feeds the food
chain is right there for them. Great.
>> Thank you. Councilman Cra,
>> I do have one followup. Okay.
>> Please. Um, we were provided a a map
here. I'm not sure you have it. I'd be
happy to give you mine, but it looks
like there's going to be quite a bit of
development regardless of what we do
with power lines and sewer lines and
right through the middle of that. So,
that property is going to be impacted
significantly.
>> Okay.
>> Regardless,
>> right, there's there are power lines
going through there already, right?
>> Put in water. put more in. Okay.
>> All this development here.
>> So, so we'd be happy to work with you uh
to
uh mitigate the impacts from power lines
and sewer lines and maybe enhance
habitats. um by uh deterrence on the
structures so that um uh
uh raptors mostly don't nest on those um
uh really uh that would be a fairly
ideal use compared to traffic and lights
at night.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you very much.
>> Thank you, Councilman Crave.
Lori
Lori Wayne Chestnut from on Range View
and I am here speaking for Ottabon
today. Um I'm the president of the
group. You all got our letter. Um I just
wanted to make a couple of mentions
because I was at the planning committee
and to clarify why number two and number
eight were turned down uh why they were
denied. Uh first of all, the historic
nature of the ranch do we feel does not
go well with consecutively having a
business park right next door. Uh the
gentleman that spoke before us uh in the
previous discussion said that the
eastern end was nothing but box stores
when you come in. We would love to see
Wyoming Herford Ranch in that area be
highlighted as true western. So you'd
have an eastern great western kind of an
orientation and then you would have the
new cowboy museum um on coming in from
25. So that's a treasured area. So that
is why number two is denied and my
background is public health. The number
eight was where it was uh denied and we
feel it does not comply. The neighbors
were concerned about the sound, the
lighting, the vibrations. Some of the
neighbors that testified at the planning
meeting said they could actually feel
the vibrations at night from the meta
center that is I guess it's somewhere
nearby or one of the uh maybe it's the
other one across the street but there's
a lot of feelings about the public
health concerns there. Um now saying
that said we would very much like to be
at the table if that is developed. We
could do BMS. We could do more trees to
block that off from the ranch. We just
feel that the ranch is a treasured area
not only for the birds but for our
history. And we really feel that that
area should be protected and isolated.
The ultimate thing would be of course to
have it protected completely. But if
not, I think Ottabon could help a lot
making that area a lot more bearable and
tolerable. And I'll take questions if
there's any questions.
>> Thank you. Any questions?
>> Okay. Yes, ma'am.
>> Maria White Dove. I actually live out in
HR ranch. Um, I'm very curious about
these birds because we go out behind the
road that goes from camp stool around
the Microsoft facility that they built
out there. And I've noticed that there
is a decrease in the birds. We go out
there at least once a month since
Microsoft has built out there.
Have we considered taking the new land
that they want to sell? And I understand
they want to sell it. Have we considered
putting that into the greenway going up
to the archer
for the um bicyclist and hiking and
stuff
and keeping it more natural and not
making it into a big business or data
center. I don't see our community
reckoning events director um Mr. Sanchez
here and I don't know if he's online but
that would fall under his um purview in
his department and um maybe Mr. Bloom
can speak to that.
>> And chair, members of the committee,
Charles Bloom, planning and development
director. Um, at this time, our parks
and greenway planner has not looked into
any purchase or acquisition of that site
for open space.
>> So, the answer would be no at this
point. Yeah.
>> Okay. Is there a way we can pause until
we can look into that? Because I know we
passed a lot of money for greenways
recently.
That's a I mean that is definitely a
conversation.
>> Madam Chair, we I mean we've got several
more weeks here.
>> Yeah.
>> Before this would ever be finalized. So
we have an opportunity to look into it.
>> This is our first hearing of this in our
committee. So um yeah, we but thank you
for that idea.
>> Thank you for the time.
>> Thank you for being here.
>> Any other public comment,
>> Madam Chairman? Um members of the
committee, uh my name is Larry Wolf. I
represent Ward One uh on the city
council and I rise um just for a couple
points. Uh number one is to encourage
you to go out and look at this parcel.
Uh I've been out there now several
times. Um it is that it really is the
last remaining parcel undeveloped as you
come into the city from any direction.
And as Representative former
representative Samuelson said, they're
all ugly from every other direction. And
what I'd hate to see is that this parcel
gets developed sort of by default
and not and because we have a failure of
imagination,
we should think broadly about how this
parcel could be used for any number of
things that aren't a truck stop, aren't
a data center, aren't a retail store. Um
and um and as you come from the east
over that hill down into the city, which
is where you first see it, data centers
now all along the right hand side of
that and then this open parcel.
We should take advantage of having plan
Cheyenne
uh which is going to be looking at all
of this and give them an opportunity to
consider that over the next year.
Doesn't sound like there's really any
rush from this. I understand this is
private property. I understand the loms
certainly uh would like to see it, but
the community has an interest in this,
not just in uh a conservation aspect for
the birds, but as a sort of piece of
land that might be a very welcoming
gateway
development um that could serve a lot of
public purposes.
um well beyond having another place to
buy a cup of coffee or uh buy your
gasoline. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Any other public comment here
in the room?
Good afternoon.
Hello,
Madame Chairman.
Councilman,
thank you for your time and opportunity
to address a concern yet again.
This really doesn't seem to me to be
>> Can you identify yourself? Sorry.
>> Oh, I'm sorry. For the record,
>> Katherine Atkins, uh, Neielson Ranch
Road.
>> Thank you.
>> So, we're not really against
development. We understand that they
were intending to do something with this
parcel.
It would help if we had an idea what
they were going to do with it so that we
could be supportive. and as they've
offered work with the plant.
That way we would know how it would
benefit not only the city but also the
county.
Currently the industrial park seems
contained mostly to the north and to the
west. And I say why don't we contain it
there letting rather than let it creep
into these rural um HOAs and homes which
are very much valued for that. These
people have purchased approximately 164
homes currently in this area with the
idea that they appreciate the rural
quiet country setting. They very much
value that.
So one of the questions would be how
does this benefit the neighbors?
So the Herford Ranch is historic enough
to have signs literally on the
interstate announcing it. Yet, the first
thing potentially would be seen would be
something other than a rural area.
This is directly impacting one of the
oldest working ranches in the region.
And since rodeo is the new model for
Wyoming, this seems very anti-Wyoming
that, as he pointed out, every entrance
to the city is something industrial.
The other thing I'd like to point out is
the traffic flow because considering
this is an interchange of the
interstate, but it is also the uh merge
points of I80, South I80 service road,
Hails Ranch Road, and the entrance to HR
Ranch. So traffic is definitely a
concern there, not only for the
wildlife, but safety for for everyone in
that that area. So for these reasons,
when we think about wildlife, the
historic value, utilities, potentially
maintaining the character of the
neighborhood in the area, and a historic
rural setting, I would ask that you you
focus against this proposed annexation.
Thank you.
>> Thank you. Is there any other public
comment?
Any comment online, Jennifer?
Okay, I'm not seeing any. I would remind
everyone that again this is only our
first uh stab at this and it will be
coming back again. So, um lots of
opportunities to have those important
conversations.
Um so I would entertain a motion.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I move to approve on
second reading.
>> Okay, we have a motion from Councilman
Crave to approve.
>> Second. and a second by Dr. Renie. Any
com any discussion?
>> Go ahead.
>> Yeah, Madam Chairwoman, I guess I sit
here and list this and I I understand,
but I guess I'm going to look at it more
narrow narrowerly.
Um,
we have a landowner that wants to
develop their property and we have
people that either live adjacent to it
or have an interest in it and
essentially would like to use us to veto
a sale or property use. And it and I've
actually heard you comment once that you
know and I've said it too, if there's a
vacant piece of property near you that
you want it to stay vacant, you need to
own it. So,
um,
to I that's still my attitude, Madam
Chairwoman. I guess if, as I said, if if
you want if there's a group of people
that want it to stay that way, they
should be buying it. Otherwise, again,
you have a land owner that wants to
develop and there's
um,
you know, there's there's no reason we
shouldn't be able to let them develop
their land to as they wish to do it. Um,
so at this point I'm going to support
it.
>> Thank you, Councilman Crave.
>> Madam Chair, through you
again, it's very early in this process.
Um, but if I were ever to look at a
piece of land and look at the
surroundings for it and the request to
develop it commercially,
this is it. I mean, you got a business
park on the north. You've got uh the
power plant that's going to expand. It's
going to expand fivefold.
That's that's what's before the
Industrial Sighting Commission right
now. I I believe it's going from 140 to
>> megawws.
>> Megawws. Um
you're right at I mean it's literally at
the interchange uh camp stool and I 80.
I mean just holistically
that's a that's a business park.
Now, there's other factors that that
you've all brought up. Um,
so I guess the question is between now
and the next time we hear this,
hopefully you're going to meet with your
group and and see if there's any
interest in purchasing it and perhaps
uh we can meet with the developer or the
owner and see if there's possibilities
of minimizing any impact that they may
have. Uh, so I think there's more work
to do on this. Um,
but generally speaking,
I mean, this just I forgot that there's
another uh substation going in right on
>> Yeah,
>> right on Camp Sto.
>> No, that's the power plant. I think this
is the the new substation they were
talking about. So,
>> um I I'm going to let it I'm going to
vote for it today and we'll continue to
work on it for the next couple weeks and
uh see if we can't find out more
information. So, thank you very much.
>> Hey, Councilman Lebornne.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman.
I agree with the planning commission and
believe that this is a an action that
should be should be uh denied. And the
reason I believe that is what's the real
reason that we have zoning
no matter where it is. And the argument
that if someone believes that that zone
change is inappropriate,
uh they should go buy the property.
We'll think of that application
throughout the city. Um that's just uh
not really much of an answer in my
opinion.
I hope everyone here uh takes a look at
this property as I have done along with
Mr. Wolf. It's a narrow piece of
property with a power line across it, an
interstate right there,
and a
importantly
nestled there in that industrial area is
the historic ranch
that has been preserved by that family
uh in excellent condition. And I can't
help but reflect on what happened out on
the Cox Ranch that was abandoned and is
now in ruins.
So that's a factor here.
The birds I think are very much a factor
as well.
And so when we look at this
um to me the real determination is
when we when we do the business park
designation
along with it comes a use by right
of a facility that [clears throat]
admittedly is across the Interstate 80
there.
But is this really where we want to be
building a very unique
uh effort here which is the uh
a data center. Is this the place for a
data center
by right?
No, it is not.
And I hope everybody thinks about that.
There's a reason we have zoning.
it is compatibility with the surrounding
area. And I certainly recognize and
understand that there's a a lot of
development right nearby there. But a
data center at that site to me is an
example of the data center gold rush
we're experiencing right now. We can put
one here, we can put one there,
and we have to really consider if
they're appropriate in all situations.
And in this particular case, um this
relatively narrow piece of property with
the power line, uh with the other
development nearby
is a case where we can look at it and
say
not here.
There's opportunities uh for data
centers that are being exercised
throughout the community,
but to grant this a use by right to have
a data center
is really where we need to stop and
think about it. And when we think about
it, we realize that
um perhaps
uh there's a limit and the limit should
be right here. So, I believe that uh the
idea that anyone who believes
that our zoning uh
is
relatively unimportant
and that our planning commission is
needs to think about it because that's
the purpose of zoning. This is an
inappropriate site for a data center and
this is where we make our choice. Thank
you.
>> Any other comments?
>> Yes, Dr. Renie.
>> Yeah, I did have I did want to go back
um I think it was Mr. Donley that talked
about the aquifer. I wanted to address
that. If
>> with this being annexed
>> Bowman or Bowman
>> maybe I wrote the name down wrong.
>> Yeah. Um, with this being part of the
city, whatever happens there has to be
on city sewer and water. And um, 70% of
the city's water comes from the west
slope, 15% come from wells, 15% comes
from reservoirs. So really if any
development in the city is not going to
have much of an impact on on the
aquifer.
Um I I I
mean to me it seems like our our plan
and if we go with what the plan was and
what the zone was um or recommended zone
was that CB that's still commercial
development. And so,
um,
you know, if if they'd come through with
a CB plan, our staff would have
recommended that and and perhaps our
planning commission then would have
approved that. And if it develops
commercially, to me, I mean, I realize
with the business park, the data center
is a possibility.
But if you look at the work that um, Vio
West and Skybox and now Traml Crow are
trying to do to to accommodate neighbors
in the area, they're trying to reduce
lighting. they're trying to reduce
noise. Um it seems to me like a data
center would have much less of an impact
than than a commercial development or
truck stop would in that. So I don't
think um the data center is the worst
possible scenario for that piece of
property. Finally, I know my comments
bought if you want to control it by it.
I do think that's accurate, but that's
probably seems kind of harsh. There
there are there are things that we can
do and the developer can do or the
things that we can require and the
developer can do in the way of
landscaping and buffering and I would
hope that as those discussions go along
our planning office would take that into
consideration
um that the developer would take that
into consideration too because I'm there
again I think there are things and we
don't know what's going to go there
either everybody's assuming it' be a
data center, but there are there are
ways to mitigate those impacts. So, I
would hope that the city and the
developer would seriously look at those.
Thank you.
>> Thank you. And I I think what I heard
you say, Dr. any uh in that statement is
that uh there is a huge opportunity here
for um the AHR land management group to
reach out and have a conversation with
the neighbors and with the Ottabon
society and the people that are involved
so that we can start that communication.
It sounds like maybe there hasn't been a
lot of that that's taken place so far.
So, um it would be helpful to know. So,
thank you. Any other discussion?
Okay. hearing or seeing none. All in
favor say I.
>> Opposed?
>> No.
>> This item will move forward with a
recommendation to approve at the next
meeting of the council. Next item,
please.
>> Number 14, ordinance, second reading.
Annex,
west of South Gley Highway, south of
West College Drive, and southwest of and
adjacent to the intersection of Apple
Street and York Avenue. So, um, as we
get ready for the staff report on this,
um,
are you you ready? Okay. Thank you.
>> Yeah. Thank you,
>> madam chair, members of the committee,
Connor White, Planning and Development
Department.
>> [clears throat]
>> the application before you it's for
annexation. Um so this is the first item
on the agenda of multiple uh that are
basically all under one project. Council
has seen a lot of these lately where you
get multiple items. Uh so this is the
annexation portion. So we're looking at
um basically should the land be annexed
into city limits. So the proposed
annexation is for 162.42 acres of land.
Uh this is west of South Gley Highway,
south of West College Drive and
southwest of and adjacent to the
intersection of Apple Street and York
Avenue
uh this area. And I'm just going to go
ahead and I will go through the criteria
because I feel like I'll probably get
that question from Councilman Crave. So
I'll do that ahead of time with the
staff report. Uh so with criteria number
one um an annex basically it goes with
the an annexation of this area is for
the protection of the health safety and
welfare of the persons residing in the
area and in the city or town.
So with this uh with the annexation um
should this land be annexed it will
receive city and fire protection and
sanitary services uh would be extended
to the area. should note that with this
property there is water and sewer
already adjacent to the land. Um so they
would already have access to city of
Cheyenne water and sewer. I believe at
the public hearing it was brought up
something about South Cheyenne Water and
Sewer District. This would not be on
South Cheyenne Water and Sewer District.
It's not within that district
whatsoever. It would be on normal city
of Cheyenne water and sewer. Um,
basically the water and sewer was
extended with the meta uh data center
that's to the south.
So with criteria one services would be
provided um and are available to be
extended into the area. Having access to
water and sewer instead of relying on
private wells and septics reduces
long-term groundwater impacts uh that
could affect uh basically downgradient
properties. So staff does believe it
meets criteria one. Criteria two, the
under or the urban development of the
areas sought um of the area sought to be
annexed would constitute a natural
natural, geological, economic and social
part of the annexing city or town.
Um right now the land is currently
vacant um or possibly used for
agricultural uses. Um the land
surrounding surrounding it uh is either
residential development to the north
northwest. you do have vacant land on
both the west and the east and then
industrial to the south. So annexing the
land would benefit those uh who live in
the areas. It does bring um in city
services but then also
however uh whichever way the land
develops it does provide economic
development opportunities uh for the
city um and eventually does become a
social and economic fabric of the city.
Number three, the area sought to be
annexed as logical and feasible.
Um,
basically same reasons as I've already
discussed. It's adjacent to city limits
already. It has city services available
to it. Um,
this the nearest fire station is I
believe fire station 2. And then this
one also the water is along the west
side and south side and then you have
sewer along the east side.
So again it has city services adjacent.
So by annexing it becomes that natural
um kind of extension and is logical for
the reasons that it has services
available.
Number four is the contiguity. It's
25.26%
uh contiguous. Uh that's all along the
south end of the property.
Uh franchise utilities are in place.
That's number five. And then number six,
we did mail uh within the time period.
Again, I know at the public hearing is
brought up that people receive their
letters after the required date. State
statute requires that the mailing go out
by a certain date, not that they receive
the letter by a certain date. So, I just
want to clarify that as well that staff
did notice actually ahead of the
required mail by date. Um, but again,
with mail, it does take time to get to
people. Uh, it's not instant. So, most
likely, um, people did receive that a
couple days afterwards.
So, staff does believe that, uh, all
state statute requirements are met for
the annexation and does recommend
approval of this annexation. And I stand
for any questions.
>> Thank you. Yes, Councilman Crave.
>> Briefly, Madam Chairwoman, um I know
staff has mixed feelings on how it
should be zoned, but as far as
annexation, whether it's developed as
residential rooftops or something else,
it's you staff does believe that it's
better to be part of the city rather
than wells and septics and part of the
county. Is that right,
>> Chairu? Uh that is correct. and um
because I'll end up going through a lot
of that when it comes to the zoning and
the future land use on how staff
reviewed those. But regardless of how it
develops, um it should probably develop
within city limits. It is within the
urban service boundary. Um so it is
within an area that we believed would at
some point annex and develop in some way
and be a part of the city. So regardless
of how it develops, um yes, staff
believes that it should be annexed into
city limits. One followup, please. Uh,
I've attended several public meetings
for this and um
members of the of the city have said
several times that if this is annex,
this would not um
allow annexation of the Orchard Valley.
In other words, there would not be
enough uh surrounding Orchard Valley to
require that we could force annex. Is
that correct? I want to get that on the
record.
>> Chair through you. Uh that would be
correct. This doesn't change Orchard
Valley's contiguity to city limits
already. Um, it doesn't change it.
Basically, it would not create 100%
surrounded, which is what the city has
done for county pocket annexation. When
we've looked at pockets is generally
it's areas that are 100% surrounded.
This does not change that percentage.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you. Uh, Dr. Renie,
>> no ma'am.
>> Oh, it's okay.
>> So, just a reminder, we are talking
about just annexation at this point. So,
>> [snorts]
>> um, yes, ma'am.
Good afternoon, Madame Chair, members of
the council. My name is Megan
Kronikfeld. I'm with Triml Crow Company.
Um I'm here to just um firstly thank
staff and Connor for his um analysis of
the annexation and and his presentation
here. Um I'm here to speak in support of
the annexation of the 162 acres at
Orchard Hills. um approving this
annexation is really in the best
interest of um the city and and the
property in terms of next steps for the
potential development of this property
for all the reasons that staff has
outlined. Um we are here to answer any
questions. I know there's more
conversation regarding zoning um that
will come up and we are we're available
to um provide comment and answer any
questions there as well, but I want to
thank you for your time and your
consideration here.
>> Thank you.
Is there any other public comment?
Um, and when you um come up to speak, if
you could just tell us whether you live
um in this Orchard Hills area or not, we
would sure appreciate it.
Any other public comment on the
annexation?
And I don't see anyone online. Do you
see anyone online, Jennifer?
Okay. Not hearing or seeing any. I would
entertain a motion. Madam Chairman, I
would move to approve on the second
reading.
>> Hey, we have a motion from Councilman
Crave.
>> Second.
>> We have a second from Dr. Renie. Any
discussion?
>> Councilman Leborn.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. Um,
I speak in favor of this uh annexation
because of the extensive effort that
went in on the part of Treml Crow to
really come up with some answers to
questions that uh I believe are central
to development
uh the rapid industrial development of
South Cheyenne.
and uh this particular parcel and what
uh Traml Crow is willing to do to help
the community. So what I'm looking at
here is I think everyone probably has it
is the commitment to the Cheyenne
community between the city of Cheyenne
and Crl Crow. So when you talk about um
we are only to discuss annexation,
does that mean we can't discuss this
commitment to the Cheyenne community
that has been prepared through a lot of
effort to deal with these issues? I
would uh say that we will discuss any of
that under zoning because most of these
items apply to zoning
rather than annexation in this um
commitment to the Cheyenne community
document.
>> Well, I understand your ruling. Um
I believe it's incorrect.
That's
>> and when we talk about the zoning, we
talk about the development of this area
which is an important [clears throat]
piece of how we look at uh data center
development.
The slicing and dicing of the
considerations here I believe are
incorrect.
>> Duly noted.
So,
>> did you have any other comments on
annexation, Councilman Labor?
>> Yes, I do. I think we should proceed
with this annexation. And the reason I
believe we should proceed with this
annexation is the very matter that
evidently I am not to discuss at this
time.
Thank you.
>> You're welcome. So, we have a motion and
a second. So, all in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed. This item will move forward
with a recommendation to approve at the
next meeting of the council. Next item,
please. Number 15, ordinance, second
reading, amending the official zoning
map of the city of Cheyenne,
establishing the zoning classification
AG agricultural for land annex to the
city of Cheyenne, located west of South
Gley Highway, south of West College
Drive, and southwest of and adjacent to
the intersection of Apple Street and
York Avenue.
Okay. Staff report, please.
Chair, members of the committee, Conor
Way, Planning and Development
Department. So, like we always say with
any annexation, there's always the
assigned zoning. We give it the closest
zone uh to that uh of what it is in the
county or the current use. Um currently,
this property is LU in the county land
use. Uh the land use zone district in
the county allows for multitude of
different uses. Um,
a lot of it is either conditional or
they have various things you have to go
through for certain uses surrounding it.
Uh, you do have light industrial to the
south. There's residential uh to the
north and then more LU zoning both to
the east and the west.
Currently, this property is vacant. Um,
looking at the size of the property and
looking at just the area around it,
the least intense zone district to go
with would be the egg zone. Um, I know
we always say it's sometimes used as a
holding zone. Uh, but when staff looks
at assigning the a zone for properties
when they do come into the city, that is
our least intense zone district. Uh, so
we're not just flat out giving it say a
commercial zone district um or something
like that depending on the area it's in.
Uh that's generally why we go with the a
zoning for a lot of properties when
they're annexed unless it's very clear
that that property is surrounded by
other zone districts that are already in
the city. Um because it is the least
intense zone district to start with. So
staff does recommend the AG zone for
this parcel uh upon annexation. Planning
commission did hear this at their
September 8th meeting and did recommend
approval of the the assigned zoning. And
with that, I do stand for questions.
>> There any questions from committee here?
Councilman Labbornne regarding the AG
annexation
>> or I'm sorry, zoning.
>> Um,
I think I'll
Okay. If if you're going to recognize me
now for this purpose, I appreciate it.
We have come up with uh
a commitment to the community that's
extensive. I've attended the meeting out
in the neighborhood.
Uh I think whether we
talk about it this time or we talk about
it another time,
it's important to note that uh and and
it has been noted earlier in our meeting
here
that we've come a long long way in our
understanding of what should come into
the city and how it should come in from
what we were discussing and uh ignoring
ing uh this spring. So, I want to point
out that uh these individuals
who are proposing this project
have really taken a look at the
particularly important to me is the
greenway in the neighborhood and agreed
to connect the greenway to the larger
system at their expense.
They looked at the roadway system and
how it can be improved.
They looked at how they can help uh that
Orchard Valley neighborhood with their
water system and help them with uh a
variety of uh activities that will
enhance that neighborhood. So
um
I'm not sure how we are handling it uh
today. Madame Chairman, are we uh are my
comments the extent of our adoption of
this uh commitment to the community or
how are we to wrap this into our process
so that there's some true meaning
associated with all the effort that went
into this from the people who want to
develop this and and of course I also
want to note that uh this the the
contiguity is important um in this
zoning question and perhaps we'll be
looking at it at the next item coming up
here. But um this is this project is
contiguous to the project next door to
it,
>> the meta project. So, Councilman Leborn,
um my intention would be to um discuss
the A annexation or the zoning to A
right now and then when we go to the
next item which would zone it to for the
um final use which I believe is light
industrial that we would then discuss
the commitment to the Cheyenne
community. Although my understanding is
this is just a rough draft document
that's still in process and is not being
considered under this particular zoning
um action.
>> I think I've made my point, Madam
Chairman.
>> Okay. Thank you. Any other questions
from committee for staff or comments?
Okay. We'll open it up to public
comment. And again, this is on
annexation to agriculture.
Okay. Are there any online, Jennifer?
Okay. Seeing or hearing none, I would
entertain a motion.
>> So moved. Second.
>> We have a motion from Councilman Labour,
a second from Councilman Crrave. Um, any
discussion
hearing or seeing none, all in favor say
I.
>> I.
>> Okay. All opposed. This item will move
forward with an op with at the next
meeting of the council with a
recommendation to approve. And now we're
going to move into the next item, which
is the zoning to light industrial.
Connor number 16, ordinance, second
reading, amending the official zoning
map of the city of Cheyenne, changing
the zoning classification for land
located west of South Gley Highway,
south of West College Drive and
southwest of and adjacent to the
intersection of Apple Street and New
York Avenue from AG Agricultural to Li
Light Industrial.
>> Thank you, Jennifer. Now, staff report.
Chair, members of the committee, Connor
White, Planning and Development
Department.
The application before you is for
resoning uh from the established zone of
AG to light industrial.
Now, there are basically two other items
on the agenda that come later because
they are resolutions that do deal with
this zoning. So, I'm going to kind of
have to go through those a little bit
and I'll go into more detail when we get
to those items because they are
basically essentially together. um when
it comes to
one how council should review this and
how they should think about how they're
going to vote. Um because there's a
future land use map amendment. Without
that future land use map amendment um at
least the way that staff reviews it, it
would not without that future land use
map amendment being approved, staff
believes that it wouldn't meet criteria
1 2 5 and 8 um for a zone change.
So, when reviewing for the light
industrial zone, um on the future land
use map, currently this area is
uh projected to be mixeduse residential.
Uh that would look at basically being a
mix of residential uh whether it be
single family, multif family, mixeduse
developments, whether it have com some
commercial um
lighter commercial, more heavier on the
residential side, but it could be a
mixeduse development. So that's what the
future land use would predict this area
to develop as.
So in reviewing for the zone the zone
change um
the
request to light industrial does not
meet the intent of that mixeduse
residential zone from the future land
use standpoint. Um again because that
mixeduse residential would look at that
residential use or commercial use rather
than an industrial style use.
The area surrounding this uh the only
city light industrial is to the south
that is the metadata center. Um
otherwise you have
again the LU zoning on the east and the
west in the county which the LU allows
for a multitude of different uses.
uh through various processes and then
you have predominantly residential to
the north.
Also, when reviewing this and this kind
of gets into the future land use uh
designation as well, um
understanding that
to the south is light industrial and the
mix the land use plan was changed for
that data center development. When staff
reviewed uh that proposal back in 2022,
um part of the review was that hopefully
by that area changing and allowing for
that development, it would bring those
utilities to hopefully spur further
either residential development or other
development in this area.
So again, it's it's kind of hard to
fully go through the zone change uh
without really diving into that future
land use designation. Um but ultimately
with the future land use when we went to
planning commission, we gave planning
commission that option. They reviewed
them and we gave them basically if they
approved uh the future land use, then we
told them that they should recommend
approval of the zoning map amendment.
Ultimately, uh, planning commission did
not approve the future land use. So,
they did recommend denial of the zoning
map amendment as well. Um,
so with that, staff does recommend
denial at this point. Um, unless council
moves forward with kind of overruling
planning commission and then going with
the approval of the future land use. If
the future land use is approved, then
staff would recommend approval of the
zoning map amendment. At this time,
planning commission did recommend denial
of the future land use map amendment. So
ultimately, staff would recommend denial
of the zoning map amendment.
With that, I am available for any
questions.
>> Councilman Crave, can you unwind that?
>> Madam Chair, I I'll try
the land use amendment. This the staff
gave four reasons why
this should not be considered for
industrial development. I I don't know
whether I should take
my arguments against the four reasons
now or later. I'm I'm surprised we
didn't
I'm surprised that the land use
amendment came before the annexation
today. We're doing the annexation and
now then we're going to go talk about
the land use amendment or should I talk
about staff's four reasons for denying
the land use amendment now because it
directly impacts
the annexation? What which would you
prefer?
I'm sorry. It becomes a chicken and an
egg situation, right? So, um, yeah. So,
I would be open to how you would like to
proceed.
>> And I'd like to look look at the four
reasons staff gave. Um, number one,
beneficial and addresses issues. U, the
staff said the city of Cheyenne has a
housing shortage and it may not be
appropriate to remove areas designated.
Uh, Mr. White, the report you rely upon,
uh, when was it when was it produced?
Madam chair through you. So if we're
talking about plan Cheyenne, that was
2014.
>> 2014. So it's 12 years old. Have there
been changes in South Cheyen in that
period of time?
>> Madam Chair through you, changes as in
just development patterns and
>> activity development. Yeah,
>> madam chair through there there have
been changes. Um so there has been the
industrial change that I mentioned with
Meta going in uh when again when staff
reviewed that. Well, well, Madam Chair,
I think when you look at this particular
parcel,
to the south is a is the meta project.
To the north, there's currently one
electrical substation. There's a second
one, I believe, is either in the process
or soon to be built. When you look to
the west, there's a railroad line. Um,
I'm not sure that if anybody wanted to
develop
housing, specifically single family
housing in this area, that they they
could do it. Who would buy that?
I mean, staff has has hung their hat on
this being a residential property.
I don't know of a developer that would
risk millions of dollars for the
infrastructure. Um, with the surrounding
um industrial use, particularly to the
south, I'm not sure you can ever sell
those lots on the south side. But, but
staff has hung their hat on that one.
So, I I disagree with uh staff criteria
number one. Criteria number two, combat
com compatibility with surrounding area.
I don't I don't understand how you could
say that the commercial property would
not be compatible
with the whole southern border
is meta.
There's 16in pressurized gas pipeline
running down the west side of this. Um,
so I I'm I'm lost on your their criteria
there. Criteria seven, strict adherence
to the plan. I mean, we're going to
stick with the 12-year-old plan
regardless if the neighborhoods change.
That's basically what staff is telling
us. Um, I'm not sure that's that's
appropriate either. Finally, finally,
public welfare and consistency, the
domino effect. Uh, I think the domino
effect has already occurred. Um, I don't
think
denying this would stop the domino
effect. So, I personally disagree with
your four criteria and your analysis of
it. Thank you.
>> Any other questions for staff?
>> Okay. If not, we'll go out for public
comment.
Good afternoon, Madame Chairman and
members of the committee. My name is
Cindy Delansancy. Um, I'm here on behalf
of Trimel Crow. I know Mr. Nakushima is
with us today online. Um, as we
discussed with you, unfortunately, he
had a uh out of town uh family vacation
planned before this matter was
scheduled. So he is here. He is
available for discussion. However, he
was unable to be here in person. Um
Madame Chairman, I too
kind of follow along the lines of
President Crave and Council Member
Lebornne as far as please stop me if I
get into a a discussion for another part
of the agenda. That's certainly not my
intent. I know that Jennifer has our
exhibits available and I think they're
really relevant to build on some of the
analysis that was put forth um by staff
and then ultimately reviewed. That's
what was put before the planning
commission members. We very much
appreciate your staff and we very much
appreciate the members of the um
Cheyenne City Planning Commission.
However, I don't think they got it right
this time and I say that with all due
respect. But the full picture needs to
be analyzed in the matter that is before
us today and careful consideration
um should be going to kind of where we
are in looking at this full picture. I
do have the entire Traml Crow team here
with me today. If we have some questions
about that, I would like to come back to
the community commitment agreement that
council member Lelaybornne discussed and
and we're more than happy to answer any
questions about the project. I will try
to keep my um remarks short. Um we have
Megan and Jay and uh Riley uh and Jake
with us too. Again, the whole team is
here plus Mr. Nakushima online.
Basically, in a nutshell, again, we
think that the planning commission just
didn't have a full
current snapshot. They were very hung up
on this concept of that this parcel
should not be change its zone should not
change because of the availability of
residential inventory. I'd like to take
you to exhibit number one uh as well uh
as the public. Um at the time that this
discussion took place uh madam
chairwoman this exhibit was not
available to the planning commission for
their examination. What this exhibit
shows is that the red pieces are just a
snapshot. Further analysis has been done
that we even have an up more even
current one. But this is showing the
thousands of acres that are available
for residential inventory assuming like
five homes per acre in a medium density
to single family. Um there is enough uh
land available
in the current inventory assuming this
small lot that is at issue the subject
property here today would come out of
that inventory to last for another 60
years of residential construction.
The subject property the little square
in exhibit one madam chairwoman is
amounts to 2.4% 4% which actually again
we have another board over here that I'm
happy to bring over for the council's or
for the committee's consideration but
this this kind of notion that we should
not change the zone because this is
inventory for housing unfortunately we
feel that it just wasn't the full and
complete analysis
um some of the factors to support this
is that the city of Cheyenne has been
working diligently to develop velop
these areas designated for residential
development and the city's done a very
good job of this. We have adequate
inventory in all quadrants of our city.
Uh currently there are three large
acreage zone for residential on all
corners. We've talked about exhibit one.
The highlighted acreage provides two
24,875
homes for residential development.
uh reviewing the previous 5-year average
of single residential home absorption of
3 to 400 residential building permits
issued per year. Again, this is where
that 60 years of inventory comes from.
um the the the change in in the zone
would not meaningfully impact Cheyenne's
future housing supply and should not
amount to the basis of a denial for the
requested zone change that is currently
at issue before uh this committee for
recommendation. The requested zone
change is consistent with the character
of the area which brings us to the
second criteria as far as compatibility
for the surrounding area. Uh if we could
maybe go to exhibit number two,
Jennifer, thank you very much there. As
you can see, Madame Chairwoman, on this
uh the area around the subject property,
it's neighbors to a 900 acre data center
campus. It has high powered gas lines,
high voltage two two high voltage uh
overhead transmission lines, water
lines, um sewer lines, substations,
railroad tracks, and industrial
development. This subject property makes
sense to be contemplated for the zone
change that's being proposed.
Um it is it is really the most effective
and practical way to achieve the plan's
broader objectives. The delivery of
critical infrastructure is also a piece
that is um is really important to this
subject property. Uh the transportation
network envisioned in the staff report
will only materialize through
highcapacity industrial investment.
Constructing essential arterial and
collector roadways specifically for the
full buildout of the wall road and
Parsley Boulevard carries an estimated
cost to 10 to 15 million to complete.
This off-site burden is is likely
economically prohibited for residential
homebuilders under current market
conditions. Strict adh strict adherence
to residential zoning would leave these
critical roadways and sidewalk
connections unbuilt and unfunded
indefinitely. Private industrial
development is uniquely capable of
absorbing these capital costs into a
project turning plan rights way into
paved modern safe corridors.
superior pedestrian and student safety.
Again, knowing that um the staff report
points to uh the nearby Aphabach and
Rossman elementary schools and as well
as the um new 56 school, Mountain View
and Triumph High School to justify as
part of the justification and
residential uh of justification of the
residential zoning. However, a typical
home 600 home single family subdivision
would generate approximately 5,000 to
6,000 daily vehicle trips concentrating
on heavy commuter traffic on local roads
during peak morning drop off and
afternoon dismissal hours. When you look
at the proposed project that we are
considering, um a secure data center
campus generates virtually zero peak
vehicular traffic and no school hour
conflicts by pairing uh negligible
traffic volumes and newly constructed
modern roadways and protected crossings.
This project creates a measurable safer
environment for neighborhood pedestrians
and students than residential
subdivisions could apply.
Um, council member Lelaybornne talked
about the greenway extension that is
being proposed. I direct your attention
to the upper corner that little looks
almost kind of like a like a fish hook.
That's also uh something that is being
contemplated to add um uh we're willing
to commit to extending the Cheyenne
Greenway from its current uh area to
southwest southeast corner of Orchard
Valley through to the northwest corner
of Orchard Hills. This expansion will be
funded and delivered in direct
coordination with the city's greenway
program, providing a permanent amenity
for surrounding community that
residential development again could not
deliver. Additionally, the developer is
pro proposing a 560 ft deep vegetated
burm as a buffer to the residential
areas to the north that will serve as an
amenity to the Orchard Valley
neighborhood. A mitigator of light and
noise and with viewshed enhancement
enhancement. Um the next uh slide is
exhibit number four. Jennifer, if we
could maybe roll to that one. The next
one. There we go. That that's what that
burm would look like. Um, and then
again, the fence would be on the other
side of the burm, giving that
connectivity to the greenway for for
neighbors and opening up a really nice
amenity for the neighborhood in Orchard
Valley. Um, and then the rendition of
what that burm would look like is
located there. Uh, and you can see low
water, natural vegetation, mature trees
to be a very nice viewscape for the
entire community.
Going down to criteria number eight as
far as public welfare and consistency.
Um you know ample housing inventory
exists to meet the future needs and and
in my client's view public welfare
includes economic health. Public welfare
is not limited to housing supply. It
also includes economic opportunity,
employment and a strong tax base. A
multi-billion dollar data center project
significantly promotes public welfare
through economic investment.
Um, as the domino effect mentioned in
the staff report should be framed
positively as a strategic cluster of
high-tech employment that makes Cheyenne
a regionable regional hub for digital
for our digital economy. This is a
planned outcome. This is not merely by
accident. Low concern to the community
as evidenced to the staff report as
well. staff has received one inquiry
from the public on this project and a
letter supporting the proposed change.
Um the project page has at this time
that we prepared this viewed over 165
views with no comments. We have engaged
in multiple uh public uh open community
conversations. We've enjoyed those
conversations with the community. it.
There's a sense that the community would
much rather have a project such as I
just described with uh the Burm and and
the secure area as opposed to
highdensity residential as contemplated
in the staff report.
Um so for those reasons uh madam
chairwoman just to kind of keep my
comment short we feel that um the um
denial in the staff report the denial of
the planning commission on the land use
map and the zone the future the
amendment of the future land use
amendment as well as the zoning perhaps
those decisions were not made with with
the full information today. Um, Council
Member Lelay in in closing, Madam
Chairwoman, brought up this document
that we've been hard at work at. We've
had the community weighing in right with
us on this. Some of the things that um
are outlined as far as what the project
is versus what it's not are contained in
this document and of which I'm happy to
share with anybody interested. But this
agreement, this commitment to the
community talks about the description of
the project, its intended uses, the
jobs, the traffic impacts, environmental
impacts, restrictions on development
related to water, restrictions on
development related to the design and
cooling systems, specifically stating in
bold letters that evaporative cooling
will not be utilized in this project.
also mentioning that the um Black Hills
energy large power contract service
tariff um insulates from res residential
folks from any type of um increased cost
or shifted cost. The the agreement
contemplates use of lighting, sound,
setbacks, landscaping. And then the the
part that I am I'm very proud of and
really do appreciate the residents of
Orchard Valley for their input in this
is that it talks about at this point in
annexation what the developer sees and
this is not an exclusive list. This is
an initial list as as how to be a good
neighbor and a good corporate citizen.
Those in those items just right off the
bat are installation of a new water well
for the Orchard Valley neighborhood,
Orchard Valley Community Center
upgrades, road improvements within
Orchard Valley neighborhood where where
requested, Orchard Valley neighborhood
communicate community bene
beautifification fund. So, if somebody
wanted to cut a tree down or um build a
ramp if you're bringing a handicapped
family member home, um you know, do
something that you don't necessarily
have the funds, a person in the Orchard
Valley neighborhood would be able to tap
into those funds to make sure that they
would be able to beautify their property
in the way that they felt best. We
totally voluntary. Nobody would be
forced to do anything, but the resources
would be there if needed. In addition,
the greenway expansion, we already
talked about that. That is a exciting
project that I think would be wonderful
for the southside as well as also this
this uh governing body has heard a lot
about sidewalk improvements in South
Cheyenne to improve school walkability.
That is specifically articulated as one
of the ways that um Treml Crow can be a
good community partner, a good corporate
citizen, and most importantly, the best
neighbor it can be. trash disposal,
workforce housing, traffic study, snow
plowing, fire mitigation, all of these
things are clearly identified in writing
so there's no misunderstanding of what
this project is and how um it could be a
benefit of the community. I really do
appreciate the time to give the um
committee that update, Madame
Chairwoman, and respectfully request
that um that maybe that this uh
committee and hopefully the governing
body will take a a different approach
that was looked at in the staff report
and then the decision of the um planning
commission as related to zoning.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you. Any questions?
>> Okay. Um, and can you just tell us where
we are at with the community agreement?
Is it has it been signed? Is it in
process? Is it
>> Thank you, Madam Chairwoman. We um we
have one small edit that was detected
today in our meeting uh and is ready for
execution um when you know at next
reading, certainly before final reading
on this matter, but it is ready to go
with that um slight amendment that was
identified in in a meeting this morning
that unfortunately just popped up on us.
It's just a one sentence that needs to
be stricken. So, it's available.
>> Thank you.
Okay, we'll go to this side.
Um,
it's hard to know without knowing what
the question is. So, go ahead.
>> I'm sorry. So,
>> can you identify yourself for the
record?
>> Donna O'Donnell from Orchard Valley. and
and you know to tell you the truth um
madame chair was nice enough to give me
a copy of this commitment to the
Cheyenne community. I wasn't aware that
that had been in a draft form and um and
I was at the coffee which I learned a
lot of information from but did you meet
with anyone in Orchard Valley on this?
The person that was here earlier waiting
to talk was from Orchard Valley Water
and we showed it to him and he had not
seen it. Could you tell me who you've
met in Orchard Valley regarding any of
these?
Madam Cheron, through you to Donna, Miss
Donna. Yes, we have met with them. The
landowner is here. Mr. Nakushima is
online. There's been a lot of
discussions. Um, if you're looking for
names, I can get those to you now. Mr.
Nakushima can talk to you about this.
But when I was there the other night,
two of the committee community members
that have been working on this did stand
up uh and talk about the well and the
pieces that of that have been inputed in
here.
>> This is Kevin.
>> Yeah.
>> And uh he said he didn't see this yet.
So I'm just curious where this is in the
game plan. You know that he was not
aware of it and he just saw it before he
left. And he's a vice president of
Orchard Valley Water. So I I'm just
wondering I'm on Orchard Valley Water.
I'm just wondering how this is all
working and with the city madam
chairwoman through you. Um as far as
handing out this document at the open
meeting, we did not do that. However,
that's where the documents or the inputs
related to what was needed for the
community and requested by community
members. That's where that section was
developed. Uh we do have another open
house coming up in two more weeks and
that's hopefully where we can continue.
Um we have been asking for feedback for
anybody that would like a draft or
review a draft but this did this did not
just um come out of thin air. This has
been discussed by with multiple parties,
multiple people and feedback given and
we just look forward to continuing if
there's additional feedback and when you
get to online I bet you that uh Mr.
Nakushima might have more to offer to
Donna's questions as well. Madam
Chairwoman,
>> I would appreciate it. Mrs. Dansancy, if
you will make sure you get your contact
information.
>> Thank you. Okay,
next person. Mr. O'Donnell, did you have
You were next, I think, at that podium
before your wife stepped in.
>> Andy O'Donnell. I live in Orchard
Valley.
>> Um, I I think this
what uh Mr. White did here. I think I
don't understand your zoning. You have
the criteria for zoning and then you
bypass it or you [clears throat] change
it
and uh it doesn't make a whole lot of
sense if you've got got rules to follow
the people who are going to use this
land or for one thing or another.
It's spelled out and then you change it
without any input from anybody else
apparently. So
if you're going to have rules, follow
them. You know, you're going to make
changes and adjustments
based on
a whim.
See what happened at Meta that looks
like a disaster.
Uh if this is what you're going through
from here on out, make everything look
like Meta, then you're way behind the
curve on that. There's people in
Lancaster, Pennsylvania, city there has
agreements, enforcable agreements of
people put it in data centers. And I'd
like to see the city council latch on to
that kind of stuff. So you protect the
people who are in the community
and people are affected by your
decisions
and you have information that you want
to bypass and ignore.
I don't think you're doing a very good
job of what you should be doing.
>> Thank you,
>> Madam Chair. Can I respond, sir?
>> Sir, we have taken input from all of
your neighbors. I've been at several
meetings there. We've taken a lot of
input. I think I think we're going to
hear from more of them today. Uh but to
say we have not taken input,
I think is totally inaccurate.
>> And we do have and we do have a
document. We've been discussing it that
will be binding.
>> Well, why do you have a uh planning
commissions who say this does not live
up to criteria and that's the
information you're looking for?
>> Well, as I pointed out,
>> ignore it.
>> As I pointed out earlier, sir, I don't
agree with their analysis.
>> Well, just because you don't agree with
it doesn't mean it's wrong.
>> Well, in my opinion, it is.
I'm sorry, but in my opinion, I pointed
out four on the four criteria why I
thought their criteria was wrong,
>> why their interpretation of it.
It doesn't make any sense. It's just
you're just going to do whatever you
want to do
and pay no attention to what's out
there.
>> And we will have additional uh this will
come back um before committee um again,
right? So, um, there's still time to
have input. So, thank you for being here
today. Yes, sir.
>> Uh, Ross Ginsel, 2405 Draper Road. I am
on that property line and, uh, just as,
uh, Councilman Labour had said, uh,
Praml Crow has done a fantastic job in
my opinion as far as their care for our
community and what they're what they're
offering us. Um,
we were dreading highdensity housing
because of the noise uh the the
incredible increase in traffic and what
safety that uh endangers the children uh
that may be raised in this area. But for
myself, I'm have a law enforcement past.
from I'm a retired law enforcement
and
residential crime. When you put a
highdensity housing area or something on
that line, residential crime greatly
increases
um
along with noise
uh and Treml Crow's plan as far as the
uh the buffer, the green buffer there is
fantastic.
um
keeps the animals, the wildlife there,
um it protects us from the noise and the
the lights. Uh
so
unlike some of the folks who don't live
on that that property line,
um some of the folks behind me do as
well, we're all for the data center.
We're all for that light industrial
because of what it's going to provide us
and
what it's not going to do. That makes
sense.
>> Thank you.
>> Good afternoon.
>> Good afternoon, madame council.
Councilman, thank you for having me
here.
I disagree with the planning committee
and I totally agree with um Councilman
Crave as far as it not meeting the
criteria to go to light industrial.
I disagree with the any housing
developments back there for the same
reasons because of the power lines
because of the railroad because of the
other data center which
which was a huge disaster.
Grandma Crow has met with uh neighbors
both in my area and inside of Orchard
Valley. Our property line is right on
the prop against the property line in
question and they have been really good
about listening to our concerns and and
making changes accordingly to be a good
neighbor. They would not be anything
like meta. they would have uh benefits
of being there. Putting housing there
and causing a lot of [clears throat]
increased traffic dumping out on two
roads on West College Drive, it's
already tough getting out on College
Drive. But to add two two more high
points there with high residential
um working with Traml Pro, they have
alternatives
obviously a whole lot less traffic going
in and out but also an a roadway to
South Kley and a roadway
going up with the extension of Parsley.
So it would disperse
any traffic and it wouldn't impact us.
We'd still have some natural habitat in
the area and it would increase the
greenway.
But quite honestly, I like to bike ride.
I'm terrified to bike on South Gley or
College Drive. And I love the greenway
and extending the greenway.
I'm all for that. Keeping natural
habitats or berm. I'm all for that. I've
been there since two I've owned the
property since 2000. And we have horses
in the area and we have, you know, goats
and chickens and things like that. So,
it it would just totally impact us to
keep it as residential. So, I vote that
we go to light industrial.
>> Thank you.
>> Can you identify yourself for the
record? Oh, I apologize.
>> I'm sorry. I forgot to ask you,
>> Susan Gensel.
>> Okay. Thank you, Susan.
>> Thank you.
>> Thanks for being here.
>> Yes, sir.
>> All right. Good afternoon, Orlando
Flores. I live on right on the property
line, 2404 Draper Road. I just want to
say I have two little girls, so I'm
against the residential and the big for
a big reason. You know, traffic. I I
feel like it's a very safe place right
now when if you go step in my front
yard, you see one or two vehicles and
that's delivery drivers. If you put high
high density residential, what's going
to happen? I can't have my daughters in
the front yard. I can't I can't leave
them unsupervised for a little bit
because I don't know who's passing by.
We don't know who those people are that
are coming in. And with working with the
data center, we know who they are.
They've been very open with us and they
they all they want to do is help help
our community not lose its value, which
is how quiet and calm it is. So, we're
I'm all for it with for the data center.
>> Thank you. Thanks for being here, Mr.
Flores.
>> Yes, sir.
Hi. Good afternoon.
>> True. Um I live at Plum and Draper. It's
about 200 yards north of both of these
folks here. Um
I really think what Traml Crow is
proposing is are to be good neighbors.
Um we haven't seen that from Meta. They
seem to be more of a bad neighbor. Um
this whole buffer that with the
landscaping would be would not only be a
buffer between us and the new data
centers but between us and Meta as well.
Um I could only see that as being a
benefit to us. We hear people talk about
Orchard Valley
and a lot of the folks from Orchard
Valley love to tell us that Orchard
Valley ends at York Street.
So, we are not in Orchard Valley.
They're in the uh the Shockley
subdivision.
I'm in the San Ray subdivision,
but this doesn't touch Orchard Valley
directly except for one little tiny
corner.
Um, so you know, I don't see
see that part of it being a big deal.
Um, what I'd hate to see the the big
residential in there for the same
reason. The roads in or or the area are
not designed for the amount of increased
traffic. And I don't see any way without
extending Draper North all the way to
college, right through the campground,
through the New Harington's pub, you
know, to to get to college. And and
5,000 extra trips a day through that
neighborhood would just be a disaster
for us, I think. And and really I'd like
I you know I haven't been the biggest
proponent of data centers because I've
seen meta and I've seen the ones that
just come in and and make a mess of the
landscape but Traml Crow is proposing a
thing that I think will benefit the
neighborhood and I'd really like to see
see things move in that direction. Thank
you.
>> Thank you.
>> Good afternoon.
>> Hi
Amanda Pelto. I live adjacent to the
back side of the property. I also share
uh fence line with Meta and um I am
definitely for this this change. I've
lived out there for 27 years and I think
that this is the best use of that
property.
Um I know Meta does get a bad rap um you
know sharing a border with them um this
entire time. um I haven't experienced
any of those common complaints of noise
and um being a bad neighbor and and
things like that. So um Tramble Crow is
a breath of fresh air as well because
they're adding extra benefits to our
community.
Okay, thank you.
>> Thanks. Any other public comment?
Okay, we'll look and see if there's
anyone online that would like to make
public comment.
Hey, hearing or seeing none, I would
entertain a motion.
>> So moved.
>> Oh, sorry.
I'm going to say his name wrong.
Nakushima.
>> Yeah, he um he chatted but he didn't
raise his hand. So, I'm just going to
allow him to talk. Is that okay?
>> Sure.
>> Maybe.
I can hit the right button.
>> Madam Chairwoman, can you hear me? Okay,
>> I can. Thank you, Jeff.
>> I just wanted to address um Donna's
Donna's question earlier. Um Donna, I
apologize when I saw you on Thursday
night that I did not send it the next
day. I was out of the office or Friday
and today, but I I will explicitly
follow up with you on that agreement.
But just just to be really clear, um you
know, talking with Kevin um among, you
know, numerous other Orchard Valley
residents, those those bullet points
that Cindy listed off of the ideas that
we wanted to present um and based on the
feedback that we've heard that would be,
you know, the greatest impact, the
greatest benefit to Orchard Valley um is
is what populated that document. So I I
um and I think Kevin would attest that
too. And I understand that, you know,
there there is a long road and, you
know, a bunch of additional
conversations that we would need to have
um, you know, to make sure for like on
Thursday night for example, is the well
8 in? Is it 12 in? You know, all the all
the the design and everything else that
would come to that. But I think the most
important thing is that we want to put,
you know, our our, you know, foot
forward and say we are raising our hand
saying yes to this in writing. Um, and
and being, you know, completely
transparent. And again, I think Cindy
said it best of, you know, what this
project is and what this project isn't.
So again, Donna, my my apologies for for
forgetting to send you that, but I I
will literally get that to you right
after we get off this uh meeting.
>> Thank you.
Um, okay. We have a motion of on the
floor from Mr. Leborn and a second from
Dr. Renie. Is there any discussion?
Mr. Labour?
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. Um,
we've had a lot of discussion here of
the commitment to the community.
Is it your interpretation that that is
to be added to the zoning uh regulation?
Uh my understanding is that that is um
still being negotiated or finished up
and that that it would be presented um
before the final third reading
>> of the zoning.
>> Yes.
>> Well, um we've had some discussion about
this previously and uh I believe it's
important that this all come wrapped up
in the annexation.
Um, and we really can see here that
those individuals
who dedicate their time and effort to
our planning commission
um do so in a sincere and dedicated
effort.
They were confused
by the fact that we have fallen way
behind in our planning in general.
And furthermore,
that in the specific elements that we're
facing here today
and elements that are adjacent and part
of this proposal like the greenway
connection that someday will run down
division to the school. There just a
tremendous number of issues that need to
be coordinated in an area that's part
city, part county,
and that really needs obviously is just
the meeting that was just held with W
dot a lot of roadway issues. It really I
hope we've progressed here. I hear that
we have and um certainly that's a good
thing.
But surely the next step is a more
comprehensive approach
and a real further understanding of the
magnitude of this development
because this issue shows us what can be
done.
But then we look down the road at some
of the
massive
issues that are coming with the power
plant
with the whole approach to all this. So
where is madame chairman and members of
the committee where is the overall
repository
of a comprehensive understanding of
where we are and where we need to go?
I don't know where it is.
And unfortunately, when we're in the
position that we're in right now, we
have members of the council
going out and searching for information,
we have a lot of
intense opposition
to this entire development of data
centers. When that ship sailed, I mean,
and it is gone. We're going to be doing
it. How we do it is the question. And I
would suggest that this commitment to
the community and the effort that's gone
in uh certainly was something that I
wasn't aware of at first, but as we went
through the process, I began to see how
it really was uh sensible. And I think
that that's part of my concern that I've
expressed before
that is a that is a condition of
annexation. Is it logical and feasible?
And that that's an interpretation we
make. So I definitely make the
conclusion here that this matter is
logical and feasible. I'm concerned
about some of the process. But uh this
is an example I hope we're going to see
more of and that is really um
important because it it frankly madam
chairman it's easy to get run over by
these trillion dollar corporations.
So we want to make sure that we're
listening and communicating. And to do
that, we need a better process and we
need that information to be readily
available not only to us but to uh the
public as well. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Any other Yes, Councilman
Crave.
>> Thank you, Madam Chair. I agree with my
colleague from Ward One. Um
as we've gone through this journey, um
we've learned a lot. Um, I think this is
the the best rendition we've seen yet,
even even compared to Skybox we heard
earlier. It really started uh with
Microsoft when they had their public
meeting out at LC. I think that was
maybe in May. Um, but we've progressed
to just a ton of public and neighborhood
meetings. We've progressed to written
documents setting forth specific
issues that the neighborhood and others
have brought up. Um
I've attended several of the
neighborhood meetings. Um I think the
realization of the residential
development
and the
um issues that come with that um really
hit a reality. Um you know 5,000 trips a
day through through the air through the
current neighborhood. That's that's a
lot. I my house backs up to Yellowstone
and it gets 16,000 trips a day and
that's a lot. So, um the impact that
would happen to the current community as
compared to
the proposed development,
uh I think those issues have been
discussed extensively by the neighbors.
um the the group we saw today, the vast
majority are in support of the uh the
development, the burm,
um all the all the benefits that come
with this. Um I'm going to I'm going to
support it. Uh I do want to make sure
that the agreement is refined and
finalized
uh before third and final reading. Uh
somehow we need to make it a part. I
don't know where.
ask the attorney.
>> Maybe that's a lawyer question.
>> Uh
but uh I definitely definitely need to
make that part of the overall package.
So I will support it today. Thank you.
>> Dr. Renie, any comments? Okay. Okay. All
in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed? This item will move forward
with our recommendation to approve um at
the next meeting of the council. Next
item, please.
Number 22. Resolution amending the
future land use map of plan Cheyenne by
changing the land designate the land use
designation from agricultural rule open
space and parks and mixed use employment
to community business and removing the
natural and cultural resources area
designation for property generally
located south of Interstate 80,
southeast of Otto Road and west of
Interstate 25.
Staff report please. Morgan Dennis,
Planning and Development. Um, this is a
future land use map amendment for the
Hitching Post District. Currently, the
area is designated as agricultural
rural, open space and parks and mixeduse
employment. And the proposed change is
to community develop community business.
This request is to allow a zone change
to BP business park. While the BI BP
zone district typically has the
development patterns of Swan Ranch and
Northr Range Business Park with
commercial and service uses are
typically sec secondary uses and or
support industrial development in the
area. The BP zone will be undergoing uh
changes to its allowed agricultural
uses. Um, one of the identified uses for
the hitching post district will need the
allowance to develop equin facilities
which is going to be proposed.
This proposal is compatible with the
area and how it's currently developing.
Surrounding development includes
commercial development to the north and
east while parcels to the south and west
are vacant. The current land use map.
The current land use in the surrounding
area is to have
industrial and mixed juice employment
development. Commercial development here
will be taking advantage of the
interstate interchange and support
industrial development further south.
This would promote public welfare
because it would be an increase in jobs,
development of water and sewer systems
and tr and the transportation network in
the area. Planning Commission heard this
item on September 8th on September 8th
and recommends approval. This also went
to the county commissioners Tuesday,
September 15th and the only comment was
is that they support the Hitching Post
district as a whole.
Um there has been no public comment
regarding the future land use map and I
stand for questions. Thank you. Is there
any question from committee?
Okay, go up for public comment. Any
public comment,
anything online, Jennifer? I don't see
anything.
Okay,
I would entertain a motion.
>> Move. Second.
>> We have a motion from Councilman Labour
and a second from Councilman Caggrave.
Is there any discussion?
Hearing seeing none, all in favor say I.
>> I. opposed.
>> I did hear the discussion some
>> there wasn't any after the staff report.
>> Oh, I did hear the discussion.
>> Okay. Thank you. Okay.
Um, moving on to the next item number
23.
Number 23 resolution overruling the
planning denial of PUDC-26-176
a future land use map amendment from
mixeduse residential to mixeduse
employment.
>> Okay. Staff report please.
>> Chair members of committee. Conor Way
planning and development department. Uh
you have seen these before. Uh basically
we have to have this resolution prior to
the resolution for the change for the
future land use map amendment. Um it's
basically approving this allows you to
then discuss and approve the actual
resolution to change um the future land
use map and that is due to planning
commission recommend basically denying
the future land use map amendment at
their uh planning commission meeting.
So with that that's what this resolution
is based on how the zoning map amendment
went. staff would recommend that you
approve this uh resolution. Um so that
the next item can then be discussed and
basically move move forward. Um I should
note with the next item we will probably
be recommending that that be postponed.
Uh but this one you can actually go
ahead and just approve and let it be
approved at the next council meeting. Um
I'll explain more with the next item why
we need that postponed. Um but with this
staff would recommend approval of it
based on the recommendation for the
zoning map amendment.
>> Thank you. Are there any questions from
committee?
>> Okay. Go out for public comment. Any
public comment on this item?
Anybody online? Jennifer. Okay. Hearing
or seeing none, I would entertain a
motion.
>> I would move to adopt.
>> Second. We have a motion from Councilman
Crave, a second from Dr. Renie. Um, any
discussion?
Hearing none, all in favor say I.
Opposed?
>> No.
>> Okay. This item will move forward with a
recommendation to approve the next
meeting of the council. Next item,
please. Number 24. Resolution amending
the future land use map of plan
Cheyenne, changing the land use
designation from mixeduse residential to
mixeduse employment for property
generally located west of the west of
South Gley Highway south of West College
Drive and southwest and of and adjacent
to the intersection of April April A
Street and York Avenue.
Okay, staff report please.
>> Chair, members of the committee,
Connorway Planning Development
Department. So this is the future land
use map amendment resolution. Um I
briefly went over or well for the most
part I went over what staff's
recommendation would happen at planning
commission. So I'm going to keep this
brief especially due to the fact that
city council did recommend approval of
the zoning map amendment. Um you would
have to also approve this future land
use map amendment moving forward.
So ultimately with based on council's um
recommendation for the zoning then staff
would recommend approval of this uh
future land use map amendment. This was
recommended for denial by planning
commission but again the last item was
that overruling. So moving this forward
staff would recommend approval for today
though we do need to postpone this uh
two weeks so that it lines up with the
annexation itself. Um, this only went to
county commissioners for comment only.
So, we can't change land uh that is
basically outside city limits. Um, I
should probably note actually with the
item for the hitching post, we probably
should have postponed that as well. Um,
you can do that at council come next
Monday, but um, you might have to pull
that off and do that because that is
also outside of city limits. Um,
so with that, staff would recommend that
this be postponed today for 2 weeks. Uh,
because it is a resolution, but we do
put it on basically the agenda. We
learned from our past mistakes as well
that this should be on the agenda so it
can be discussed along with the rest of
the items that go along with it. Um, so
that's why it's on the agenda, but we
would request that this be postponed two
weeks to line up for third reading of
all items.
With that, I am available for any
questions if there are any. I know these
processes can get very confusing.
>> Thank you. I see Mr. Hopinson back
there, so we may call you into action
here in a minute, Mr. Hopinson. So, are
there any questions from committee for
staff?
Okay. Any public comment?
Hearing or seeing none uh here in the
chambers or online, I would entertain a
motion. Chairw I move to adopt.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion to adopt and a uh from
Councilman Crave. Madam
>> Chairwoman second from Dr. Winnie.
>> Sorry.
>> That's okay.
>> Madam Chairman, I would move to postpone
for two weeks.
>> And we have a motion to postpone from
Dr. from Oh my gosh. From Mr. Crave and
a second from Dr. Renie. Um so we'll
have any um discussion or public comment
on the postponement of this item. Is
there anyone who'd like to make a
comment on postponing this item?
I don't see any online either. So, we
will go ahead and um vote. Um any
discussion from the committee? All in
favor of postponement say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed? Okay, we're are back on the
main motion. Oh, no. We're not going to
do that because we're postponing. Um Mr.
Hopinson,
my question for you is, are we able,
since we just passed that last one that
should have been postponed, are we able
to take that action in this,
can we go backwards
or
do a postponement? At this point, he's
back in the back row there.
He just thought he was going to get off
easy today.
I have just one.
>> Uh, madame chairwoman, David Hopkinson,
deputy city attorney. So in in short
because it is the same meeting you can
move to reconsider uh and then uh change
the action that was taken um in
consulting with with Jennifer it might
be best to do that at the end of the
meeting uh just for kind of
recordkeeping purposes.
>> I Okay, I just know that we also have
some members that
have another commitment. So I'm just
trying to figure out if we will have
people around long enough to do that. So
okay, thank you.
Okay. Uh Dr. Renie, are you going to be
able to stay with us? Okay, thank you.
Then we will do that at the end of the
meeting. Jennifer, please don't let me
forget.
>> Um number 25, resolution granting
special use approval for a gaming center
pursuant to unified development code
section 2.2.7 2.7 and granting local
approval of a sightsp specific
application for a simal casting permit
to be issued by the Wyoming Gaming
Commission pursuant to Wyoming State
Statute 11-25-210
for property located at 1734 Meadowland
Drive. Hey, staff report please.
>> And chair, members of committee, Charles
Bloom, planning and development
director. Um, this is the an application
for special use for a gaming center,
which essentially is a historic horse
racing facility that would be located at
1734 Medlin Drive in the former Old
Chicago restaurant. Um, the applicant is
present. Um, so they will be able to
answer any sight specific uh questions
or development specific questions. Um
the reason this is coming in front of
the governing body is a result of our
recent amendments we did to our unified
development code to essentially move
this type of approval from the board of
adjustment to the governing body. Um
once an application is filed with the
city for this special use, it is
immediately scheduled um after a 30-day
comment period um by the county
commissioners uh for the governing body
to consider. Um as part of this we are
looking for compliance with two
elements. One are unified development
code requirements for development. Um
and those are some sight specific items
such as um is there an adverse effect on
uh child care uh facilities nearby um
other types of uh items and such. Um, in
addition, we're also looking for
compliance with state statute, which is
uh was recently modified under Senate
File 45, which requires local approval
um of this gaming center. So, in the
resolution, you will see that there are
actually uh two two topic areas that are
addressed for this one use.
Now, this one is a little bit unique. Um
it did come in for use approval um under
a different process um in front of the
board of adjustment and that ultimately
was denied. Uh that was the one of that
was the last uh historic horse racing
facility that was considered by the
board of adjustment because now that use
no longer exists and a new use has been
created with this new process. So the
governing body will be looking at this
new gaming center use under a set of
different criteria that is different
than what the board of adjustment had
looked at. Um the applicant has
indicated with their submittal um that
they did take uh notes on what the board
of adjustment found uh concerning um and
they have made amendments to this
application and actually enhance their
application to address some of those
concerns and to present it to you. the
the the governing body. Um, with that,
uh, staff has reviewed this application.
We've reviewed it for compliance with
the unified development code, um, and
also with, uh, state statute. And we do
recommend approval of the resolution
um, that's in front of you today.
>> Thank you.
Any questions for staff?
Okay, we'll go ahead and open this up to
public comment. And I see that we do
have our um partners developers here. So
if you would like to make any comments,
we would welcome that and thank you for
your patience.
Please,
>> Madam Chairwoman, council members, uh
good afternoon. Uh my name is Mark
Schlang. I'm with Bali's uh design and
development group and just want to uh
augment what uh Mr. Bloom just uh
identified were some of the concerns
that uh came up in the uh board of
adjustment hearing and just uh uh just
want to uh want to stress that we're
very excited about this project. Uh
we've uh uh BAS as a company is
obviously investing millions of dollars.
were developing the new racetrack uh in
the county and uh we were looking uh at
this location to be our uh launch
complimentary launch to that facility.
Um we've already invested about a
million dollars just in this property
and uh just really want to touch on a
few of the enhancements. I don't know if
you've had a chance to drive by there,
but we've already made a significant
difference to the to the building. We've
replaced all the roofs. We've uh
addressed all the exterior stucco uh and
exterior paint. Uh we've enhanced uh uh
we're uh in preparations we've got an
enhanced landscape design uh
specifically adding another row of trees
along the east boundary. There were some
concern about again exist uh additional
buffering against the residential side
of the east uh the east boundary. So,
we're proposing additional uh landscape.
Um, unfortunately, we missed our
planting window. So, we will bond that
and look to plant uh in the springtime
when it's appropriate to do that. But,
uh, if you drive by there, you can see
it's uh it's already a significant
difference uh to that to that corner.
Uh, the picture that you see right now
uh in the upper left is uh the current
condition of the property. So, uh we're
we're very excited about this location.
uh the uh the team uh just briefly the
team that we've assembled uh uh I've
personally worked with uh some of them
for almost 30 years. Uh we have a
Wyoming contractor. We're using local
subcontractors. Uh a lot of our design
team have a lot of ties to Wyoming. A
lot of UW grads. Um uh so uh we we feel
like we're not coming in as strangers.
We feel like we've got uh uh a team that
has some connection to uh to the
community and we'd really like to put
our best foot forward and and show you
that we're we're very serious about uh
uh uh bringing a first class facility on
all fronts. And if you look at our
investment out at the racetrack, we're
bringing uh our team from uh the Arapjo
Park facilities coming down. They've
been guiding and managing the
development of that project. I think if
you get a chance to go out there, you'll
be very excited to see what uh what is
being put in place right now. So, uh
here to answer any questions you might
have or any concerns. Um the floor plan
here, just quickly, um one of the
questions was traffic. uh we're not
adding any more uh parking spaces and
and and the the reason for that is uh
from a capacity or occupancy density
were actually less seats than what was
historically there from the restaurant
side. So from a patronage standpoint uh
the demand for the the parking and
vehicle or traffic actually from our
view will be will be uh less. Uh so
there are a number of number of
circumstance. We understand that this is
a redaptation of the building. We think
it's a it's a it's a it had great bones
and we felt really strongly that this is
a strong location for us and uh uh
really the right size facility to to
launch ourselves forward. We are uh uh
we are high on this market. We're
looking to advance a number of other
locations in not only in Cheyenne but
throughout Wyoming and uh just uh very
excited to be uh be able to uh uh to put
our footprint here. So,
>> any questions from committee?
Councilman Crave
>> through you. Madam Chair, can you
describe your
what your what your site will be? I
mean, is it is it simply gaming? Will it
be food, beverage? um kind of give us an
idea of what to expect.
>> Uh we are actually bringing our uh uh uh
we're bringing our uh culinary team from
our Blackhawk property. We have a uh a
uh a um concept called the Beastro. And
so it's a very highly regarded uh
offering up in the Blackhawk market. And
so we're bringing that team and that
menu down here. We've uh reconfigured
the kitchen, what was there before a
little bit. So, if you remember the old
Chicago, we've moved the bar around.
We've uh consolidated the kitchen, but
uh uh it's a uh
augmented American beastro type
offering. Uh so, yeah, there'll still be
food there. Um uh it it's gaming. I
mean, we're not can't hide that. It's
gaming. So, a lot of that will be in
it'll be internalized. We don't have any
program for the outside of the building.
So, if there was any concern about
flashing lights or you know what you
consider to be a
uh you know more of a Las Vegas style,
that's not what's going to be here
obviously. So, uh but uh operationally,
we have our uh uh VP or senior VP for
this region is here. He can talk about
operationally what what uh what they
view for that operation. But again, we
we intend to be uh best best in market.
uh we know who our competitors are and
we you know we're we uh we embrace
competition that that's that makes us
both better but um I think you'll find
us to be good partners.
>> Thank you. Yes.
>> Any other questions from committee?
Okay. Thank you, sir.
>> You're welcome. Thank you.
>> Looks like Mr. Johnson.
>> Madam Chair, members of the committee,
my name's John Johnson. I've seen me a
lot lately.
Um, we I represent 1734 Partners. We're
the property owners for this property.
And as you know, for the last 20 plus
years, this property has been a
restaurant and a bar. Um, like located
right there. And the same housing units
that were there when we developed Old
Chicago years ago are still there. And I
don't think that that was ever a
nuisance to the to the surrounding uh
neighborhood. So I would don't think
that this new use would be any different
than what we were doing. So I would hope
that you would find this favorable and
you know our partnership with valleys on
this property has you know facilitated
our future growth down in East Cheyenne.
So I'd hope that you would support this
for us. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Any questions
Councilman Renie?
>> Madam Chairwoman. So my understanding is
that this
we transferred the liquor license to the
east side of town. So will this be a bar
and grill license? Is that the intent?
>> That's my understanding. But
>> uh Madame Chair, Councilman Renie, I
believe that is the case. Um the retail
license is so we formed an we have
formed our company has formed a new
entity Capital City Hospitality which is
developing the old Big Lots building
down in East Cheyenne, Southeast
Cheyenne. Um Bales I believe is going
for um
a bar and real license.
>> Thank you. Okay.
>> Thank you. Any other questions? Council
member Renie. No, I just realized that I
think it's my understanding that this
project's somewhat connected to the one
on the east side, which
obviously there's a relationship there.
>> Yes.
>> Okay. Um, any other public comment? Did
you want to speak, sir?
>> Okay. Thank you, Mr. Johnson.
>> Thank you.
>> Any other public comment here in the
room? Any online?
Well, I have one one more question for
Mr. Johnson.
>> Mr. Johnson, I How long has that
building been sitting vacant?
>> Uh, since summer of 2024,
>> so just a little over two years.
>> Thank you. Thank you, Madam Chairwoman.
>> Thank you.
>> Hey, seeing or hearing no um other
public comment, I would entertain a
motion.
>> Chairwoman woman, I would move to adopt.
>> Second. We have a motion to adopt and a
second. Um, any discussion?
All in favor? Oh, sorry. Secret. All in
favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed.
This item will move forward with a
recommendation to adopt. Next item,
please.
Number 29D, resolution amending the
future land use map of plan Cheyenne,
changing the land use designation from
urban transition residential to mixeduse
employment for property property
generally located west of Roundtop Road
and adjacent to HappyJack Road and
amending the urban service boundary.
>> Okay. Staff report.
>> Chair, members of the committee, Conor
Planning and Development Department.
So this item, this goes along with
actually our first well I guess second,
third, and fourth items on the agenda
being we moved one ahead of the rest. Um
so this goes back to the Cox Ranch
annexation. This is the future land use
map amendment which would then support
the zone change to business park. So
this was postponed all the way till
today's date um so that it would line up
on third reading with the annexation.
So, because council did recommend
approval of the zoning map amendment to
BP, staff would uh recommend that the
governing body approve the future land
use map amendment uh to mixed use
employment uh so that it does support
that zoning map amendment. With that, I
am available for any questions.
>> Okay, any questions for staff?
>> Okay, hearing or seeing none. Uh any
public comment?
Anyone online? I don't think so.
Hey, I would entertain a motion. I'll
>> move. Second.
>> We have a motion from Councilman Labour
and a second from Councilman Crave. Any
discussion?
All in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed,
Mr. Renie, did you vote? Okay. Okay.
Thank you. All in. Um, so this item will
move forward with a recommendation uh to
approve on the next at the next council
meeting. And now we'll come back to the
item that we need to reconsider. So I
think we need a motion to reconsider the
item and a vote and then we can
reconsider.
It's number 22.
And I think to I don't I don't know if
we have to be but you didn't vote on a
Dr. Renie so right.
>> Yeah, he did vote. He came in late and
voted.
>> Okay. All right then. Go ahead. Do
whatever you want.
I did.
>> You going to do it?
>> No.
>> Let's make Jennifer happy.
>> Yes.
>> Madam Chairwoman, I would move to
reconsider item number 22.
>> Okay.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion from Councilman Crave
and a second from uh Councilman Dr.
Renie to reconsider item number 22 on
our agenda today.
Is there any um
>> We have to vote on whether we're going
to reconsider.
>> Yeah. Is there any discussion?
>> I don't think that's debatable.
>> Okay. All All in favor of reconsidering?
>> I I
>> opposed. Okay. We will reconsider item
number 22. So I don't think we need
another staff report.
>> Madam Chair, Conor Planning Development
Department. I would just
basically just may sorry for the record
I think I should just state that the
reason that this should be reconsidered
um and basically revoted on is just to
postpone it for two weeks so that it
lines up with the annexation of the
Hitching Post district so that because
this also only went to county
commissioners for comment only. Um so we
can't really we shouldn't act on
something that isn't within city limits
unless we have the
>> Yeah.
>> Hey, Madam Chairman. Yes, Council Money.
>> What I don't remember
since we've reconsidered I it should be
back on the
That should be the motion we're
considering and I don't think we have to
make a motion to adopt.
>> But let's do just to be safe, let's do
that. I would move that we adopt item
number 22.
>> No. Okay. Okay.
>> Second.
>> Okay. No.
>> Now, Madam Chairwoman, I would move to
postpone for two weeks.
>> Okay. Thank you. So we have a motion to
adopt uh from Dr. Renie and a second
from Councilman Naggrave. Then we have a
motion to postpone from Dr. Renie and a
second to postpone by Councilman Crave.
Is there any discussion?
Is there any public comment? I don't
know if we have anybody left.
Okay. Hearing none or seeing none. Um
all in favor say I.
>> I.
>> Opposed.
Okay. And so we now have approved the
postponement. We need to vote on we
don't need to vote on the original
motion. So we have completed our agenda.
Thank you for your patience and your
persistence. Have an amazing day and the
meeting is adjourned.
See, you got two hours of two extra
hours of daylight.
>> Yeah.
I know you're